<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grand assises: or, The doctrine of the last generall judgment with the circumstances thereof: comprised and laid forth in a sermon preached at the assises holden for the county of Southampton at Winchester, on Wednesday, July 28, 1652. By William Sclater Doctor in Divinity, preacher of the word of God in Broadstreet, London.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S918A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218648</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830221</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830221</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34671</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62379)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2019:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grand assises: or, The doctrine of the last generall judgment with the circumstances thereof: comprised and laid forth in a sermon preached at the assises holden for the county of Southampton at Winchester, on Wednesday, July 28, 1652. By William Sclater Doctor in Divinity, preacher of the word of God in Broadstreet, London.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by E. Cotes, and are to be sold by John Sweeting at the sign of the Angell in Popes-head-alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With errata on final page of text.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1: A sermon preached at the assises holden for the county of Southampton at Winchester, on Wednesday, July 28, 1652.</note>
                  <note>Copy cropped at head with slight loss of text and pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgement of God --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34671:1"/>
            <p>THE Grand Aſsiſes: OR, THE Doctrine of the <hi>Laſt Generall Judgment,</hi> with the Circumſtances thereof: Compriſed and laid forth In a <hi>SERMON</hi> Preached at the Aſſiſes holden for the County of <hi>Southampton</hi> at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> on Wedneſday, <hi>July</hi> 28, 1652.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SCLATER Doctor in Divinity, Preacher of the Word of God in <hi>Broadſtreet, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 5.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Wee muſt all appear before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his Body, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nemo futurorum metum cogitat, diem Domini, &amp; iram Dei, &amp; incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulis futura ſupplicia, &amp; ſtatuta perfidis aeterna tormenta nemo conſiderat: quod metueret conſcientia noſtra, ſi crederet, quia non credit omnino nec metuit, ſi crederet, &amp; caveret, ſi caveret, evaderet.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>S. Cyprian. de Unit. Eccleſ. ſect. 23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. Cotes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>John Sweeting</hi> at the ſign of the <hi>Angell</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-alley,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34671:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34671:2"/>
            <head>To the Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> 
               <hi>John Wyld</hi> L<hi rend="sup">rd.</hi> Chief Baron of the Court of <hi>Exchequer,</hi> a Patriot of Juſtice, &amp; an Exemplary Patron of true Piety; All Heavenly Benedictions.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot but be known to your Lordſhip (being ſo full and rich a Magazine of all Learning, and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) that the two main<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 King. 7.21.</note> Pillars, which as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> in <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon</hi>'s Temple, do ſupport a Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon-wealth, are<note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſtery</hi> and<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ti<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy;</hi> the one upholding Religion, and Divine Worſhip; the oth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, Order, and Civil Juſtice: Happy is that people which is in<note n="(d)" place="margin">Pſ. 144.15</note> ſuch a caſe, where both of theſe doe not as thoſe twins within <hi>Rebecca</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 25.22</note> ſtruggle together, but rather as <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> ſweetly
<pb facs="tcp:34671:3"/>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſa. 85.10.</note> embrace, and kiſſe each other: It's very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in Holy Writ, how the Spirit of<note n="(g)" place="margin">Eph. 4.3, 4.</note> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity (to ingage, no doubt, an harmonious accord between them) hath been pleaſed to denominate the perſons<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.11.</note> intruſted with either<note n="(i)" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.1.</note> Office, by one and the ſame name, ſtyling them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Publick</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Rom. 15.16. 1 Cor. 3.5. &amp; Rom. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſters of God for good;</hi> the one acting as Stewards of the<note n="(l)" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1.</note> Myſteries of God; the other as Diſpenſers of Righteouſneſſe and<note n="(m)" place="margin">Ames 5.24</note> Judgement unto men; Both by Gods own<note n="(n)" place="margin">Rom. 10.15.</note> ſending, and<note n="(o)" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And methinks, the ſerious meditation of this their ſo ſacred inſtitution, might power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put to<note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.15.</note> ſil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce the murmurings whether of<note n="(q)" place="margin">2 Tim. 3 4</note> heady ſons of<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 10.27.</note> 
               <hi>Belial</hi> (impatient even of the<note n="(s)" place="margin">Matt. 11.30.</note> eaſieſt<note n="(t)" place="margin">The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Belial</hi> is of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> non &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>jugum, id eſt abſque juge. Hieren.</hi>
               </note> yoke of the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi>) againſt them, or the repinings of other Christians not well informed, or miſtaken about either: Yea, indeed, it might prove a potent argument to<note n="(u)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> eſteem, or<note n="(w)" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> obey the one, and to be<note n="(x)" place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> ſubject unto the other, even for<note n="(y)" place="margin">Rom. 13.5.</note> conſcience of God. I can aſſure your Lordſhip, that thoſe beams of encouragement (ſeconded alſo by that learned and godly<note n="(z)" place="margin">My Lord <hi>Ed. Atkins</hi> one of the Juſtices of the Court of Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleas.</note> Judge then in the <hi>Weſterne</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with you) darted, and with ſo chearing a diffuſion diſplayed from your ſplendor, as from
<pb facs="tcp:34671:3"/>a bright ſtar of the greater magnitude, upon worthy Miniſters, whom you have profeſſed to reverence, even for their<note n="(a)" place="margin">1 The. 5.13.</note> work ſake, owning them (in your ſolid, religious, and elegant Charges given upon the publick Bench of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature) under the title of <hi>The Lords</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Ambaſſadors,</hi> holding ſuch as are found<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.12.</note> Faithfull, as the <hi>Philippians</hi> did <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> in<note n="(d)" place="margin">Phil. 2.29.</note> reputation; ſay thoſe beams, by a ſweet reflexion, and influence, ſo warmed the breasts, and revived the drooping ſpirits of the godly Miniſters, that the mention thereof proveth as an <hi>amulet,</hi> or even as an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt all preſent miſapprehenſions, or future diſconſolations: It is that which ſhall welcome your approach whitherſoever Providence may direct your Judiciary Circuit, and embalme your Name with Honour, the fragrant odour whereof, ſhall be reſented with a pious, and gladſome Commemoration in following gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p>How willingly could I now wiſh my ſelfe a <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> or a <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> ſome <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides,</hi> or <hi>Cicero,</hi> yea the Quinteſſence of all their Oratory united into one, and that as by ſome Pythagoricall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tranſmigrated
<pb facs="tcp:34671:4"/>into my breaſt, that ſo I might but in ſome meaſure expreſſe (it being a skill beyond <hi>Apelles</hi> himſelfe graphically and fully to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate) your eximious endowments and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which render you first a compleat <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and ſo by far the better and more accompliſhed <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should I mention your <hi>Ethicks,</hi> or Morall part, if <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> or the whole Chorus of the most refined Philoſophers had lived in your dayes, your practiſe might have given them exact rules for all their deſcriptions, or characters of the Vertues; or if we look unto what is any way perfect in them, there needs no better Comment on them than your practiſe, in Juſtice, Temperance, Liberality, Manſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and that Architectonicall vertue, which mainly ſteers all (for which alſo <hi>Sergius Paulus</hi> a governor is comm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded in Scripture)<note n="(e)" place="margin">Act. 13.7.</note> Prudence.</p>
            <p>In your Theologicall or religious part, as is recorded of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you are a<note n="(f)" place="margin">Act. 10.2.</note> Devout man, one that feareth God with all your houſe, a lover and frequenter of all Gods publick Ordinances, giving much Almes to the people, and praying to God
<pb facs="tcp:34671:4"/>alway; your retinue alſo, and attendants qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified after the perfect Canon of Scripture, with<note n="(g)" place="margin">Pſ. 101.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>truth,</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>fidelity,</hi> and<note n="(i)" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.5, 6, 7. Col. 3.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>ſingle-hearted</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Tit. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>obedience,</hi> and <hi>all ſobriety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In your Noble profeſſion, a Promptuary of the laws, a learned<note n="(l)" place="margin">Act. 5.31.</note> 
               <hi>Gamaliel</hi> had in ſingular reputation; in the adminiſtration of Juſtice<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 23.3.</note> upright, and<note n="†" place="margin">Deut. 1.17.</note> impartiall, and where is a meet Subject capable, full of clemency, bowells, and indulgence: A terror to none but to the evill, giving<note n="(m)" place="margin">Rom. 13.3.</note> praiſe and encouragement to every good man and work.</p>
            <p>All which conſidered, How can I but excec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly congratulate unto my ſelf the ſo unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Happineſſe of your Lordſhips favour, and countenance! eſpecially when I meditate the occaſion thereof to have proceeded from your candid approbation of theſe my weake endeavours ſhewn in this and ſome other Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, which you were pleaſed to deſire (where as you might have commanded it) to the Preſſe: The ſubject of it was ſeaſonable, I hope, for that occaſion, and generally uſefull for theſe times, intended as a Preſervative against the growing malady of this corrupt age, <hi>Atheiſin;</hi> Being ſtraitned by the time, and your important
<pb facs="tcp:34671:5"/>buſineſſe enſuing, this copious Theam, as a Camell paſſing through a needles eye, was compendiated into a narrow compaſs: If your Lordſhip doe look upon it as in it ſelf, it is too mean a preſent for your acceptation, but if on the affectionate Heart wherewith it is tendred to your Patronage, you may judg it a great one: It's ſometimes as Noble to accept ſmall things as to conferre great: ſuch as it is, it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates it ſelfe at your feet, beſeeching an entertainment, in finding whereof, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions ſhall bee enlarged for your bliſſe, Who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>MY LORD, Your Lordſhips humble Orator and Servant</hi> William Sclater.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34671:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SERMON</hi> Preached at the Aſſiſes holden for the County of <hi>Southampton</hi> at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> on Wedneſday, <hi>July</hi> 28, 1652.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REV. 20.11, 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I ſaw a great white Throne, and him that ſate on it, from whoſe face the Earth and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no place for them.</p>
                  <p>And I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great ſtand before God, and the Books were opened: and another Book was opened, which is the Book of life: and the Dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books, according to their works.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>HONORABLE &amp; BELOVED,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot but eſteem it as the great favour of Heaven, that in the revolution of a few months, the Divine Providence hath brought me again hither, and called mee to this Publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, on the ſame occaſion: I having the happineſſe to ſpeak in ſuch a praeſence, wherein not the pompe of any elaborate, or quaint Humane Oratory; but the power of ſolid and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34671:6"/>ſacred Divinity will be beſt regarded: of which whileſt I reſt perſwaded, I ſhall humbly crave your Devotions, that the ſame Hand which gave this opportunity, would adde alſo a ſucceſſe to this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>It were a facility (had I a mind to build a large Portall to my narrow houſe) to entertain your patience, a while, with a diſcourſe of this Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> wherein there are ſo many<note n="*" place="margin">Rev 5.7.</note> ſealed Myſteries almoſt, as Words, or Sentences; ſo<note n="(a)" place="margin">Mihi tota Apocalypſis valde obſcura videtur, &amp; talis, cujus explicatio citra periculum vix queat tentari: fateor me hactenus in nullius ſcripti Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blici lectione minus proficere, quàm in hoc ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuro vaticinio. Graſcrus.</note> abſtruſe Aenigma's, as none but a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Oedipus</hi> can unriddle them: Inſomuch that ſome of the greateſt, and thoſe too moſt ſanctified Scholars have acknowledged, that they had rather<note n="(b)" place="margin">D. <hi>Rainolds</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſ 4. againſt <hi>Hart. c.</hi> 8.</note> learn, than teach it: However ſome others, who to themſelves have ſeemed as the ſons of<note n="(c)" place="margin">Num. 13.33</note> 
               <hi>Anak,</hi> of tall Imaginations, have yet proved, in the iſſue, but like<note n="(d)" place="margin">Luk. 19.3.</note> 
               <hi>Zacheus,</hi> little in the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſound Judgment; and whilſt they have gone about to give other men eyes to ſee <hi>John</hi>'s. Viſions more clearly, they have been overtaken, unawares, by their own<note n="(e)" place="margin">Job 20.8.</note> Dreams, and many of them outlived the date of their weak, yet bold, and daring Interpretations: I cannot but appland the modeſty of <hi>Cajeian,</hi> (none of the meaneſt among the Schoolemen) who, after he had Paraphraſed the <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> and <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> profeſſed, thus, <hi>Apocalypſin fateor me neſcire exponere juxta ſenſum literalem,</hi> Hee was poſed about the Literall ſenſe of this Scripture, more meet for his Wonder, than his Expoſition: And good reaſon, for it conſiſting of many Propheſies of things to come, and thoſe too clothed with Allegories, and clad in Metaphors, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (to ſpeak with<note n="(f)" place="margin">Sophocles in Antig. Neſcia mens ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum fati, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſque futurae. Virgil.</note> 
               <hi>Sophocles</hi>) who could directly tell the ſenſe, till the event was ſeen? that being the beſt Interpreter of dark prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, ſith, as it is in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverb, that <hi>Bones bring Meat to town,</hi> that is, <hi>Difficulties bring Comforts;</hi> as, in <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Riddle, <hi>Judg.</hi> 14.14. <hi>Out of the eater came forth meat, and out of the ſtrong came forth ſweetneſſe,</hi> that of the Ancient being true, <hi>Paſeit apertis, excrect obſcurts,</hi> as the Lord is pleaſed to delight us with the clearer, ſo to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe us with the obſcurer parts of Holy Writ; and as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34671:6"/>Doctor of the Gentiles aſſures us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Whatſoever was written, was written for our Learning:</hi> there being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſome rills and brooks for the Lambe to wade in, as well as deeps for the Elephant to ſwim in: Give me leave, I beſeech you, (ſith not of curioſity to feed fancy, but of a zealous diſquiſition to diſcover verity, I attempt it) to withdraw the Curtain, and to ſet open the Windowes of this Text, that ſo the<note n="(g)" place="margin">2 Cor. 4 6.</note> light of divine truth, in a bright ſerenity, may<note n="(h)" place="margin">2 Per. 1 19.</note> ſhine in upon your Minds, and Hearts, to illuminate the one, and to inflame the other, for the beſt advantage of the whole ſoul.</p>
            <q>And I ſaw a great white throne, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Under which form of words we have, me thinks, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to St. <hi>John</hi>'s Viſion, <hi>The Grand Aſſiſes, held upon the Day of the laſt generall Judgment,</hi> deſcribed in variety of circumſtances, which as the carving, or enamelling of ſome curious Watch, doe exceedingly illuſtrate and adorn the ſame.</p>
            <p>And as in ſome ſolemne buſineſſe of great importance there are uſually ſome antecedaneous introductories to raiſe expectation, and win the greater veneration thereto: ſo here, we have ſomething obſervable by way of praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and ſomething alſo by way of action, or diſpatch: The Praeparation conſiſts of the ſuppoſalls foregoing, Men were dead, and thoſe dead men againe riſen, and brought out of the priſon of the grave, and ſet to the Bar: Death; and the Reſurrection from Death praecede the Judgment, <hi>I ſaw the dead, great and ſmall, ſtand before God:</hi> The matter of Action, or Diſpatch, is the Judgment it ſelf following this Death, and Reſurrection, <hi>The dead were judged, according to their works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The carriage, or managing of this Judgement is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, much what after the ſimilitude of<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t judicii ſpecies notior fieret Homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, judicandi forma ex his, quae inter Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines geruntur, aſſumpta eſt. Anſelm. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Rom. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> Humane Judicatures here upon earth; ſave onely with this odds, or difference: That in this <hi>Grand Aſſiſes</hi> in my Text, the Judges themſelves muſt then ſtand forth before the God of all Judges, even before the moſt dreadfull Tribunall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34671:7"/>of the onely Potentate, the King of Kings, and the Lord of Lords.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Regum timendorum in proprios greges,<note place="margin">Sen. tragoed.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Reges in ipſos Imperium eſt Jovis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For, howſoever it be the ſtyle of Magiſtrates in the Scripture, to bee called Gods, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. namely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in regard of the Dignity of their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; yet, though they be ſons of the moſt High, they muſt die like Men; they being, as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Agapetus in Paraen. ad Iuſtin.</note> 
               <hi>Agapetus</hi> told <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the ſubſtance, or nature of their Bodies, compoſed of the ſame brittle materialls with other men; though (as I ſaid on the laſt like occaſion) they be Gods with Men, yet are they but Men with God: ſo that all ſubordinate thrones muſt then be caſt down, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9. all Commiſſions given up, and a ſtrict account bee taken both of themſelves, and of their ſtewardſhip, even before Him, who by <hi>Daniel</hi> (who was the <hi>John</hi> of the Old, as <hi>John</hi> was the <hi>Daniel</hi> of the New Teſtament) is deſcribed under the title of <hi>The Ancient of Dayes, ſitting upon his throne</hi> [Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall and Paramount,] <hi>whoſe garment was white as ſnow, and the hair of his head like pure wool, his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheels like burning fire; A fiery ſtream iſſued, and came forth from before him; Thouſand thouſands miniſtred unto him, and Ten thouſand times Ten thouſand stood before Him, The Judgment was ſet, and the Books were opened:</hi> So <hi>Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, this great Judicature is, in this Text, deſcribed after this manner.</p>
            <list>
               <head type="tcpmilestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">The Diviſion. </seg>
               </head>
               <item>1. By the Judicatory, or Seat of Judgment, with its Epithets, or Adjuncts, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>I ſaw a throne, and that a great, and a white throne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. By the Judge ſitting on that throne, who is God himſelf, ſet forth under expreſſions of Majeſtick terror; <hi>from whoſe face the Earth, and the Heaven fled away, and there was found no place for them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. By the perſons to be judged, and that impartially, <hi>The Dead, ſmall, and great.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The Arraignment of all thoſe perſons, <hi>They ſtand before God.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34671:7"/>
               <item>5. The Indictment, <hi>The Books were opened.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. The Evidence, <hi>The things written in thoſe Books.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. The Sentence, <hi>They were Judged.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. The Rule, ordering that Sentence, <hi>According to their Works.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>9. The means of the Diſcovery of all this to S. <hi>John.</hi> and by him unto us, and that was by revelation, or ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall viſion; ſo himſelf acquaints us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I ſaw,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>twice;</hi> this viſion (as ſometime <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s dream, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.32.) was [doubled,] to ſhew the certainty and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of what he thus had ſeen: <hi>I ſaw a great, white Throne—and, I ſaw the dead, great and ſmall ſtand before God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And theſe (at leaſt as to my weak obſervation they oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre) are the proper, and genuine parts of this Scripture; the preſent meaſures of my Sermon, and your Chriſtian patience: Each of them being ſo important as they are do ſo invite your attentions, that I need not to ſtand courting your ears at all to obtain them: And ſo I addreſſe my ſelf to my buſineſſe, and that after this order, Firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with the Divinity, and the explication of the Text; and then proceeding unto the Morality, or the effectuall application of the whole: Pleaſe to favour me with your patience, whileſt I am (by Gods bleſſing) in the diſpatch of my Sermon, I ſhall be as contracted, as this deep matter, and your waighty affairs enſuing will give leave.</p>
            <p>But before I come directly to the ſeverall parts, I muſt of neceſſity ſay a few words of the ſuppoſals foregoing this laſt and Grand Aſſiſes; and thoſe are Death, and the Reſurrection; Men were Dead, and thoſe Dead men again riſen, (for ſurely not deadmen, as dead, but as riſen) were preſented to the Barre, and there ſtood before God: (Wherefore the Doctrine of the <hi>Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> and of <hi>eternall Judgement</hi> are conjoyned, Heb. 6.2.) <hi>I ſaw the Dead, great and ſmall ſtand before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mors a Morſu,</hi> ſaith<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> Hypagnoſt. contr. Pelag. circamed.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtine;</hi> No ſooner had the ſerpent faſtened the venome of his teeth on the Protaplaſts, or our firſt Parents, and his temptation bit them; but they bite
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34671:8"/>the forbidden<note n="(m)" place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> apple, and death immediately bit them again; And ſo in in <hi>Adam</hi> all dye, ſaith the great<note n="(n)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.22.</note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, in as much as he was not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus</hi> but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitas,</hi> as the Schoolemen expreſſe it, not conſiderable as a ſingle man, by himſelf alone, but as a publique perſon, repreſenting the Univerſality of all mankinde, the Nature whereof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contaminated in the firſt Fall, that infection runs ſtill as tainted bloud in the veins of Poſterity to this day; ſo that now, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Damaſcen, The whole ſublunary Creature is become ſubject to mutation,</hi> and as<note n="(o)" place="margin">Phil<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, de Mundo.</note> 
               <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to Generation ſucceedeth a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution:</hi> Had man indeed ſtood in the honour of his firſt Creation, and not blotted the eximious pulchritude, and beauty of that<note n="(p)" place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> Image, in which he was firſt ſtamped, he had needed, as no <hi>Jeſus</hi> to redeem his ſoul, ſo no <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> or Phyſician to cure his body, He ſhould have had <hi>temperamentum ad pondus,</hi> as the Philoſophers ſpeak, ſo equall a temperature in the exact ſymmetry of parts, that no qualities in the Elements, of which he is compounded, ſhould have contended for ſuch a conqueſt, as ſhould have routed him into his grave; For howſoever the Schoolemen (more curious, oft-times, to raiſe doubts, than judicious to aſſoyle them) had a conceit, that if the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had never fallen; yet the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> (the Lord Chriſt) had come in the fleſh, <hi>ad decus &amp; ornamentum generis humani,</hi> for the Honour, and ornament of the Humane nature; yet that is but the play of ſome wanton wits, it is not the plea of any ſolid judgement; ſith it diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points, at leaſt miſapprehends the proper end of Chriſts coming in the Fleſh, which was, to ſuffer for, and to<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.15.</note> ſave ſinners, even ſuch as by what Names, or Titles ſoever they are diſtinguiſhed above ground, like to the ſeverall Cheſſemen as they ſtand in the game, under ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall notions, on the table, yet being ſhuffled all together into one common bagge, they have no diſtinction in the duſt at all: But in<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 27.33.</note> 
               <hi>Golgotha</hi> (as ſaith the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb) are skuls of all fizes, as well great as ſmall: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Agapetus,</hi> for all have reaſon to ſay to Corruption, Thou art my<note n="(s)" place="margin">Job 17.14.</note> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34671:8"/>and to the Worms, Thou art my Mother, and my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: ſome Great ones, perhaps, like Teeth, may here dwell as in the mouth of Honour, eat up or oppreſſe a man and his<note n="(t)" place="margin">Mic. 2.2.</note> heritage, as the Prophet ſpeaks, grinding the face of the poor; or as <hi>Sapor</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> write Brother to the Sun and Moon; or as the twelve <hi>Caeſars</hi> divide the twelve moneths between them, waſhing their ſteps in<note n="(u)" place="margin">Job 29.6.</note> Butter, houſing themſelves like ſnails, in their gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſhels, and painting the earth as they paſſe with their ſilver ſlime, and on the Theatre of this world act their parts ſo, as they can blaſt with their breath, thunder-ſtrike with their frown, and cruſh with their ſinger; but the Interlude will end anon, and then they muſt all get them along down to Death's tiring Houſe, as well as others, as well <hi>Alexander</hi> as <hi>Dametas,</hi> fair <hi>Nereus</hi> as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <hi>Therſites;</hi> there is no remedy, they muſt unſtrip, they muſt uncaſe, and be all uncloathed, they muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change their Canopies of ſtate for coſtins, their Ivory couches for graves, their Palaces for charnell houſes, their Tapeſtry for ſhrowds, and all their embroidered Mantles for coverlets of duſt; <hi>Sic in non Hominem vertitur omnis Homo;</hi> Duſt at the firſt was mans Compoſition, and into duſt at the laſt will be his reſolution, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Homo ab</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Man is named in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ab</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Adam,</hi> of <hi>Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mab,</hi> the earth, or, the red earth.</note> 
               <hi>Humo;</hi> and whileſt even the beſt men carry about them a<note n="(x)" place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of death, they muſt unavoidably (for the aboliſhing of the remainders of Corruption, the Law in their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers) expect the death of the body, for <hi>the wages of Sin is Death,</hi> Rom. 6.23. They ſay there ſtands a Globe of the world at one end of a great Library, and the Sceleton of a man at the other end; which may not unfitly be thus moralized, though a man were Lord of all that he ſees in the Map of the world, yet hee muſt dye, and become himſelf a map of morttlity; even provant for worms to revell with in the grave: It's true indeed what<note n="(y)" place="margin">Stitius lib. <hi>9.</hi> Theb.</note> 
               <hi>Statius</hi> utters in his loſty verſe,
<q>Mille modis Lethi miſeros mors una fatigat.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Though there be many wayes to one, and the ſame<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 12.5. cals the grave <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Domum ſeculi</hi> the Houſe of age.</note> long home, yet we muſt all meet together at laſt in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34671:9"/>the ſame<note n="(a)" place="margin">Job 30.23.</note> Houſe, and in the chambers of death muſt be our dwelling: that Grammarian who can decline a Noune in every Caſe, yet cannot decline Death in any Caſe: In ſhort, this being a Doctrine which more needs application, than proof, ſith, as<note n="(b)" place="margin">In ortu ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hue ſuo, ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem nativitas proper at. S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. contr. Demetrian. Tract. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> one ſaith, <hi>Naſeimur morituri,</hi> we are no ſooner born, but inſtantly we begin to dye; as <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes</hi> had no ſooner wrote his Book of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> but ſoon after his Book of <hi>Exodus;</hi> we dye from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy into childhood, from childhood into youth, from youth into age, and from age into old age, and perhaps into dotage, and at length into the grave: ſurely, it were well, if every one of us could (as one obſerves) out of the Acroſtick Letters in the four degrees, or ſteps of mans Age, to wit, <hi>Puerit a, Juventus, Virilitas, Senectus,</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally make up <hi>Pius;</hi> that piety might be the golden thread to run through all; that we would dye before we do dye, ſo that when we do dye, we may not dye; that is, that we would dye daily unto<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom. 6.7. 1 Pet. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>ſinne</hi> by continuall mortification of all our vile, and corrupt affections, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we do dye into our graves, by a naturall diſſolution, ſo that when we do dye a naturall death, we may not dye the death eternall; which death eternall doth not conſiſt in the annihilation, or utter abolition of the Body and Soul in regard of their beeing, or ſubſiſtence, as the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures might ſancy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. but only of the ceſſation of their well-beeing, in regard of the everlaſting ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of both from the gracious and glorious<note n="(d)" place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.9.</note> preſence of Almighty God, and withall of the plunging of both into the ſenſe of torments in both unto all eternity, even for ever and ever: By this occaſion, ſith we are ſure we muſt dye<note n="(e)" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> once, and but once, as the day hath but one ſtarre, but it is the Sun, the Lyoneſſe but one young one, but it is a Lyon; ſo we having but one death, it had need be a good one: We perhaps ſecurely contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate our Naturall complexions, having milk in our breaſts, and<note n="(f)" place="margin">Job 21.24.</note> marrow in our bones, blithe, and buxom at the preſent, may be apt to ſay to the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons hereof, as ſometimes <hi>Felix</hi> did to S. <hi>Paul</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of righteouſneſſe, temperance, and judgement to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34671:9"/>come, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Goe, thy way for this time, till a more convenient ſeaſon; whereas, it may be, in reſpect of the Lords Divine Praeſcience, according to which from aeternity every mans dayes are<note n="(g)" place="margin">Job 14.5, 14.</note> appointed, it may be this night, before we know what<note n="(h)" place="margin">Prov. 27.1. Jam. 4 14.</note> to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row may bring forth, our<note n="(i)" place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> ſouls may be taken from us: But yet, if we conſummate, and finiſh a good life before Death ſeiſe on us, ſo that the thought of our<note n="(k)" place="margin">Deut. 32.29. Eccleſ. 7.36.</note> end be ſtill at the end of our thoughts; it will not be to the godly <hi>in inſidiis,</hi> as a ſnare, but alwayes <hi>in januis,</hi> under expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation as at our doors: the ſtroke of Death can never be too ſudden, when to a mortified ſoul it's alwayes under expectation; Thus, <hi>qui moritur, non moritur, quando moritur,</hi> as S.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>65.</hi> quaeſt. qu <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtine</hi> made his riddle, ſo prepared, he doth not dye, when he doth dye.</p>
            <p>Yea, he ſo dyeth, that he both is, and ſhall be ſure to live, and riſe again: and ſo ſhall all others of all ſorts whatſoever: None ever but a<note n="(m)" place="margin">Luk. 10.27.</note> Sadduce, or men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the ſame leaven, denyed it: thoſe dry bones in <hi>Ezekitl,</hi> chap. 37. which being made to live again, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving breath, and ſinewes, and fleſh drawn over with skin, did immediately indeed repreſent new vigour to be ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put into the dead hopes of the Jewes; but yet by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or moſt Divines taken notice of likewiſe as<note n="(n)" place="margin">Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr. loc. Com. Claſſ. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>82.</hi> num. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> a Type of the Reſurrection: foredenoted, ſay ſome, in <hi>Aaron</hi>'s rod, which being pluck't up by the roots, wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dry,<note n="(o)" place="margin">Numb. 17.8.</note> budded afreſh; ſo<note n="(p)" place="margin">Rabanus Maurus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in Ierem. cap. <hi>1.</hi> fol. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rabanus Maurus;</hi> hanſelled it was alſo in thoſe raiſed under the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the<note n="(r)" place="margin">2 King. 4.36.</note> 
               <hi>Shunamites</hi> ſon. and the man<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 King. 13.21.</note> who touched the bones of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> &amp;c. and ſome others raiſed by Chriſt, under the New Teſtament, as<note n="(t)" place="margin">Joh. 11.44.</note> 
               <hi>Lazarus,</hi> the widows<note n="(u)" place="margin">Luk. 7.15.</note> ſon of <hi>Naim,</hi> the<note n="(w)" place="margin">Mar. 5.42.</note> daughter of <hi>Jairus,</hi> thoſe Candidates of immortality, as one cals them; and in expreſſe texts, there is enough in both Teſtaments to evince it; both the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Cant. 4.5.</note> breaſts of the Spouſe yeeld us milk, which we may thence<note n="(y)" place="margin">Iſa. 66.11.</note> ſuck out, and be ſatisfied with as with the breaſts of conſolation: ſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.19. <hi>Thy dead men ſhall live, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead;</hi> the almoſt whole fifteenth chapter to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> is ſpent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34671:10"/>on the ſame ſubject: yea, ſome Chriſtian Philoſophers have attempted to draw as much for the thing it ſelf from grounds of regulated reaſon; even from the very deſire that the ſeparated ſoul hath to be reunited again to the body; for, confider the foul, not as abſolutely in it ſelf, a ſpirituall, immortall ſubſtance: but reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively, and with relation to the body, as it was <hi>forma in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formans,</hi> or, as by<note n="(z)" place="margin">Ariſtot. lib. de Anima.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> under that notion, it's cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that ſpecificall form, or firſt act which gave individuation to that body, which <hi>in toto compoſito,</hi> in conjunction with it ſelf, denominates the reaſonable creature Man: now, in this reſpective conſideration, the ſoul, under ſeparation from the body, which it did inform, during that ſtate, ſubſiſts in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect kinde of being: Now, as all things naturally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be preſerved in being, ſo alſo in the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect kinde of being, ſutable to the end of their firſt Creation; ſo the ſoul deſires naturally a reunion again with that body which it did inform, <hi>ratione Termini,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Term, or end of that deſire; although indeed <hi>ratione modi,</hi> in regard of the manner, and means, how this ſhould be accompliſhed, this is ſupernaturall, and requires a divine power to effectuate: The ſumme is, (for I muſt haſten to my main intention) thus all both Saints, and Caſtawayes ſhall be raiſed up, at the laſt day, the one ſort by the Spirit of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. for Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Eph. 4.15.</note> Head of the Church, <hi>quod praeceſſit in Capite, ſequetur in Corpore,</hi> He being the Firſt-fruits of them that ſleep in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.20. <hi>Cumeadem ſit ratio primitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; tetius cumuli,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> gloſſeth it, there being the ſame reaſon of the whole lump as of the<note n="(*)" place="margin">Deut. 26.</note> Firſt-fruits, in point of Conſecration, all<note n="(b)" place="margin">Reſurrexit Chriſtus, ut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrecturum ſe, non dubitet Chriſtianiae. S. Auguſt. ſer. <hi>162.</hi> de Temp.</note> members of Chriſts Myſticall Body muſt, and ſhall be raiſed alſo from their dormitories, and beds of reſt to take poſſeſſion of their Glory: and the other ſort by the power of Chriſt, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lord both of the dead, and living, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9.) ſhall be ſummoned likewiſe from their graves, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors are ſtartled from their dungeons to be<note n="(c)" place="margin">Joh. 5.29.</note> brought forth to their Executions: Both theſe ſorts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34671:10"/>like to the Letter of<note n="(d)" place="margin">Litera Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagorae diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſecta bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Humanae vitae ſpeciem preferre vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> 
               <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> (the letter Y) having two ends divided at the top, they are raiſed up, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeverall ends, according to what we read moſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely to this purpoſe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Job.</hi> 5.28, 29. (with which ſaying I ſhall now cloſe up all that I have now to ſay of theſe two ſuppoſals, or praecedaneous praeparatives to my main buſineſſe) <hi>Marvell not at this,</hi> ſaith our Saviour; <hi>for the Hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice; and ſhall come forth, they that have done good, unto the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evill, unto the Reſurrection of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi> And thus farre of what was obſervable by way of praeparation to this great Aſſiſes: wee now come to the matter it ſelf of Action, or of Diſpatch therein.</p>
            <p>In my diſcourſe of which I ſhall follow the order wherein the words are here ſet down by S. <hi>John,</hi> and then, the firſt particular, that as <hi>Abraham</hi> in his Tent, ſtands here in the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Gen. 18,1.</note> door of the Text, to invite your obſervation, is the means of Diſcovery, by which S. <hi>John</hi> came to have the knowledge of all this, and that was by Revelation, or by ſpeciall viſion; for he ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I ſaw:</hi> where we muſt take notice by the way, that he doth expreſſe himſelf, <hi>more Prophetico,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of the Prophets, in the Praetertence, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by way of anticipation, of a thing as it were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready paſt, though it was wholly future, and to come, to ſhew the certainty thereof, aſſuredly to come to paſſe, as if it had been actually paſt already, and over.</p>
            <p>But the point that we have here offered to our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration is this; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaere. </seg>
               </label> Whether in theſe dayes, Viſions be extraordinarily vouchſafed, and ſo may be expected as means of imparting to us what the minde of God is in the affairs of life, and ſalvation to the Church of God?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The better to clear my paſſage to a direct reſolution of this Quaere, it ſhall not be amiſſe on this occaſion, (but ſuccinctly) to preſent you as in a Man, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34671:11"/>wayes of extraordinary revelations mentioned in the Scripture, concerning the will of God, or the iſſues, and events of things.</p>
            <p>Theſe were either<note n="(f)" place="margin">Vid. Pet. Martyr. loc. Commun. ſect. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Oracles, or Signes, or Urim, or Lots, or Prophets, or Dreams, or Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Oracles were, when by<note n="(g)" place="margin">Act. 7.38. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> lively voyce God was pleaſed to inform his ſervants of his will, as in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary from betwixt the two Cherubims, <hi>Exed.</hi> 25.22. God was pleaſed, in the exigents of his Church to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal his will unto his people, by the High Prieſt; in this manner ſpake He to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi> and to other eminent and eximious Saints recorded for Heaven's favourites, in holy writ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omina,</hi> or Signes, by which men might underſtand his will; as in the inſtance of<note n="(h)" place="margin">Gen. 22.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi>'s offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his only ſon, in a<note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 11.19.</note> type of Chriſts owne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of himſelf,<note n="(k)" place="margin">Heb. 10.14. &amp; Heb. 9.28.</note> once for all; in <hi>Moſes</hi> typicall lifting up the<note n="(l)" place="margin">Num. 21.9. Ioh. 3.14.</note> brazen ſerpent in the wilderneſſe; in <hi>Gideons</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">Iudg. 6.37.</note> fleece; in <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s, and <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s uſing of<note n="(n)" place="margin">Ier. 27.2.</note> yokes, and<note n="(o)" place="margin">Ezek. 7 23.</note> chains, and ſuch like viſible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praeſentations of what ſhould, under certain terms expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, enſue.</p>
            <p>Urim, whereof we read, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.30. <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.21. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.6. a ſtone, or ſtones in the Breaſt-plate of the High Prieſt, which (as ſome out of<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ioſephus Antiq. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and <hi>Suidas</hi> conceive) if it became ſhining, it boded victory, or good ſucceſſe, if of a bloudy colour, warre, and if black, death.</p>
            <p>Lots were ſometimes uſed to determine doubtful iſſues, or elections, <hi>Prev.</hi> 16.33. as in the choyce of <hi>Matthias</hi> the Apoſtle, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.26.</p>
            <p>That of the Prophets is knowen, who ſometimes in<note n="(q)" place="margin">Numb. 12.6.</note> Dreams had by the Lord repreſented to their fancies, or mindes what he would have beleeved, or done, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
            <p>And the laſt way was by<note n="(r)" place="margin">Gen. 1.15. Pſal. 89.19. Prov. 29.18. Iſa. 1.1.</note> Viſions, when the Lord, either to the underſtanding, or to the imagination, or elſe<note n="(s)" place="margin">Act. 10.11.</note> viſibly to the fight was pleaſed to exhibit
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34671:11"/>the repreſentation, or ſemblance of what he purpoſed to effect; which kind of Revelation <hi>Ezekiel, Daniel, Zachary,</hi> and here St. <hi>John</hi> were acquainted with.</p>
            <p>Now, as concerning all the former ſort in uſe during the diſpenſations under the Old Teſtament, I ſuppoſe the queſtion is out of queſtion with us all about their ceſſation: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaeſt. </seg>
               </label> Wee are to enquire, whether ſuch like Viſions, (or elſe immediate inſtincts, or Enthuſiaſmes) may be expected, or will be afforded to ordinary Chriſtians, under theſe days of Goſpel-diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To which I anſwer, that Howſoever we may not tie the Lord to his ordinary means, for we know, hee can work above, yea without them; as there was<note n="(t)" place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note> light before the Sun and Moon were made; yet we have reaſons many to perſwade us, that the Lord now deals not by Viſions, or Revelations extraordinary; and whoſoever doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſuch directions, it's to be feared, they are but vain, deluſive apparitions, or dangerous, and Satanicall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures.</p>
            <p>My reaſons are theſe. 1. Becauſe the Lord hath now made perfect the<note n="(v)" place="margin">Gal. 6.16 Phil. 3.16.</note> Rule of Faith, and Life, and given us an abſolute Canon of Doctrine, to which there may no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be added, nor from which the leaſt Iota be detracted, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16. So that to inſtruct us in a matter of faith, or morall practiſe, Viſions are all now unneceſſary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For particular Events, and accidents of the Church of God, which were the uſuall matter of Viſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations, he hath given us reaſon to think, that he will no longer inſtruct his Church by that means extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, becauſe the charge runs ſo preciſely, to adde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the words of the Propheſie of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Book, under penalty of having addition made to our plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18. He would intimate in that charge, that by that Propheſie hee hath fully inſtructed his Church in all things convenient for it to know, unto the end of the world.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Even then, when was place for Viſions and Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Rule was, to<note n="(w)" place="margin">Iſa. 8.20. Act. 17.11.</note> examine all by the Word of God; ſo that if any thing came under colour of Divine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34671:12"/>Revelation, obtruded upon the Church of God, that held not currant at that Touchſtone, it was, as a probation (in Gods permiſſion) of his people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.13. So, in it ſelf, and in the iſſue, a fanaticall<note n="(x)" place="margin">Iſa. 66.4.2 Theſſ. 2.11.</note> deluſion, like to ſome Meteor, or Comet, fed onely by unwholeſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations, which ſpeedily vaniſh without heat or light; it was no say of the true<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mal. 4.2. Rev. 12.1.</note> Sun <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in whoſe<note n="(z)" place="margin">Pſal. 36 9</note> light alone it is, that the Saints of God doe ſee the ſolid light of the Truth; Wherefore, ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony; if they ſpeak not according to this<note n="(*)" place="margin">Quae libeo le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis non comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem us, ca nec noſſe debemus. Hilar.</note> Word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet thoſe grand Impoſtors of <hi>Rome,</hi> to this day, boaſt of I know not what <hi>lumen Propheticum,</hi> continued in their Church; and for moſt of their paradoxes in the queſtions of Purgatory, Prayer for the Dead, Invocation of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when other arguments drawn from dark, Allegoricall texts, or Apocryphall books faile them, at length, they come to Viſions, and Apparitions of Soules, that have appeared to the living, and teſtified, ſome, their tortures, ſome, their deliverances, by prayers, and ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Living: others pretending the lively voyee of the bleſſed Virgin from Heaven, as that, <hi>Benede me ſcripfiſti, Thoma,</hi> applauding what <hi>Thomas</hi> had written of her: at another time, ſpeaking through her image, or ſtatue in the Temple, giving the Good morrow to St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> who yet to confute the impoſture, gave anſwer, that ſhee had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s rule, <hi>It was not lawfull for a woman to ſpeak in the</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.34</note> 
               <hi>Church:</hi> But I forbear to offend your patience with theſe vanities; I only touched at them in my way, the more to faſten on all Gods holy people (truly ſuch) the perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to keep themſelves praeciſely to the written Word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by, and joined with the Spirit of all truth. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.21. even that <hi>[ſure]</hi> Word, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>Word of Truth,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.5.</p>
            <p>This of St. <hi>John</hi> was an Apoſtolicall, Perſonall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, (not to be drawn into common imitation, or into ordinary expectation) Hee being immediately acquainted of this ſecret of the manner of the laſt Judgment, by Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34671:12"/>extraordinary: It is not <hi>privilegium,</hi> but <hi>pravilegium,</hi> not a warrantable favour to be expected, but a praeſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tempting of God to be avoyded; if ordinary Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with ſleighting, or omiſſion of the Word written, do for their direction, expect Viſions now, after the propheſie of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Book is finiſhed.</p>
            <p>And thus much, if not too much, of the means, by which St. <hi>John</hi> firſt came to have to him revealed, for the generall information of the Church of God, this carriage of the <hi>Grand Aſſiſes:</hi> It was by Viſion; ſo we read in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I ſaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I haſten to the ſight it ſelf, or to what he did ſee, and that is here deſcribed, firſt, to be the Judicatory, or Seat of Judgement it ſelf, with its Epithets, or Adjuncts, <hi>I ſaw a throne,</hi> and that <hi>a great, and a white throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Throne, is a Seat of majeſty, and glory; as when <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> would be ſeen in his might, aſcends his royall<note n="(b)" place="margin">1 King. 10.19, 20.</note> throne, ſupported by twelve Lyons, the emblemes of power, and of undaunted courage: Now, whether St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw any<note n="(c)" place="margin">Vid. Geyard. e. <hi>5.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. <hi>6.</hi> ſect. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> created Seat, viſibly in ſome ſhining clouds, in the which Chriſt ſhall come, any materiall Throne, or rather ſuch a ſemblance of majeſty preſented to him, is no point of curious diſquiſition: under this expreſſion of a Throne, or of the <hi>Throne of his glory,</hi> mentioned here, and in St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> ch. 19.28. &amp; 25.31. I apprehend is meant the<note n="(d)" place="margin">Dieteric. In Feſto Converſ. Pauli, p. <hi>180, 181.</hi>
               </note> glory, the mighty power, and juſtice of the Lord Chriſt; in the maniſeſtation of himſelf as the<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1.</note> Judge of Quick and Dead, <hi>in his glorious appearing,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. or <hi>in the praeſence of his glory,</hi> as St. <hi>Jude,</hi> v. 24 It hath the Epithet of <hi>Great,</hi> to denote his Majeſty; and of <hi>White,</hi> to declare his Purity, and the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Pſal. 51.4. Rom. 3.4.</note> clearneſſe of his juſt proceedings <hi>Venit Chriſtus</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">S. Auguſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> de Symb. ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech.</note> 
               <hi>occulte judicandus, veniet &amp; manifeſte judieaturus,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7. or thus, <hi>Great,</hi> to ſhew his Severity, <hi>White,</hi> to denote his Lenity, even in the middeſt of that Severity; and both theſe exerciſed, when Actually <hi>[upon]</hi> his throne, namely, when Seated, when the Judgment, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks, was<note n="(h)" place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> ſet, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating thereby the wiſe deliberation obſerved in this finall Judicature: I might ſpeak to each of theſe, and as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34671:13"/>the Diſciples, by<note n="(i)" place="margin">Luk. 6.1.</note> rubbing of theſe eares, come to the ſolid grain, by diſcourſing on them find out the very<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſa. 63.5.</note> marrow and ſweetneſſe therein contained: Firſt, for the ſeverity of this Judge, it's to the life reſembled by <hi>Daniel,</hi> ch. 7.9, 10. when he ſaith, that his throne was like the fiery flame, <hi>a fiery ſiream iſſued, and came forth from before, him,</hi> and ſo in his wrath God is ſaid to be a <hi>conſuming fire, Heb.</hi> 12. <hi>ult.</hi> and the Pſalmiſt, to expreſſe it, in the Actuall execution, compares it to the <hi>Hills melting like wax at the preſence of the Lord: at the preſence of the Lord of the whole earth, Pſal.</hi> 97.5. To this purpoſe tends that expreſſion, in the perſon of the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Thoſe mine enemies that would not that I ſhould reign over them, bring hither, and ſlay them before my face,</hi> Luk. 19.27. Nor is it more then equall, that thoſe, who in the fury and rage of their impetuous corruptions<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 2 3.</note> teare the bonds of Chriſt's injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſunder, (at leaſt in their attempts), ſhould when he is advanced, and got into his throne, bind them faſt in<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pſa. 149.8.</note> chains, yea and though they were Nobles themſelves, in links of iron; the meaning is, to cruſh them as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> an anointed<note n="(n)" place="margin">Pſal. 2.6.</note> King; who refuſed him for a <hi>Jeſus,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming Saviour.</p>
            <p>And yet, if yee peruſe <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.3. yee ſhall there read, that howſoever <hi>He who ſate upon the throne, was to look upon, like a Jaſper, and a Sardinſtone,</hi> which ſparkled with radiant, blazing, and dazeling colours, or coruſcations; yet even then <hi>he had a rainbow round about that throne, in ſight like unto an Emerald;</hi> the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Gen. 9.13.</note> rainbow was a ſign of the Covenant of favour, after the great deluge of the old world; and the Emerald being green, and freſh, delighteth the eyeſight: Whereto tendeth all this? but to ſhew a ſtrong propenſity to mercy even in the<note n="(p)" place="margin">Hab. 3.2.</note> middeſt of ſeverity; yea, the very damned in hell find this, for though a greater judgement could not befall them <hi>Extenſive,</hi> in regard of Continnance, for it's Everlaſting; yet <hi>Intenſive,</hi> he could lay more upon them then they ſuffer: It's an old word in Orthodox Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, God rewardeth <hi>Ultra condignum,</hi> puniſheth <hi>citra con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignum, Ezra</hi> 9.13. Chriſt is ſaid in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> 1.13. to wear his girdle about his paps, or breaſt; we, about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34671:13"/>our loynes; we, about our loyns<note n="(q)" place="margin">Luk. 12.35.</note> the ſeat of Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, to curb that; Chriſt, about his breaſt, theſe at of Anger, to reſtrain it, to wit, in point of Execution; the motion of anger in Chriſts boſome was like the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of pure water in a cryſtall glaſſe, without all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly<note n="*" place="margin">His girding about the paps and breaſts ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, that there is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, or aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our Saviour Chriſt; but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thought, and inclination of his heart is kept in order by the fulneſſe of the Spirit. Mr. <hi>Ed Leigh Annot. ib</hi>
               </note> perturbation, ſuch as is in the defiled, muddy, and polluted breaſts of ſinful men; indeed, the Lord is ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe to ſnew<note n="‖" place="margin">There is a ſweet expreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>ludg.</hi> 10.6. His ſoule was [grieved] for the miſery of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> he doth not afflict [willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly] nor grieve the children of men, <hi>Lam</hi> 3.33 In all their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction hee is afflicted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. <hi>Atque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let quoties cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eſſe ſerox:</hi> Therefore in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> wee read that God as he had a <hi>red</hi> to Correct, ſo withall a <hi>ſtaffe</hi> to Support, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.4.</note> the acts of benignity rather, than the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of extreme rigour, that even when he is proceeding to the very act of Execution, his very Heart is turned within him, and his repentings are kindled together, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many expoſtulations both with the ſinner, and with his own mercy, <hi>How ſhall I give thee up,</hi> Ephraim? <hi>How ſhall I deliver thee,</hi> Iſrael? <hi>&amp;c. Hoſ.</hi> 11.8. Juſtice and Mercy ſtrive, as it were, which ſhall firſt manifeſt it ſelf; Juſtice like <hi>Zarah,</hi> one of <hi>Tamars</hi> twins, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.28. puts out the hand, on which is bound a ſcarlet thread of a blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy colour; but it draws back the hand again, till Mercy like to <hi>Pharez</hi> breaketh forth before it, and carries the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, <hi>ver.</hi> 29, 30. But I muſt haſten, yee ſee here in the Text, as the Throne was <hi>Great,</hi> to ſtrike terror into the hearts, even of the mightyeſt Potentates upon earth; ſo alſo it was <hi>White,</hi> the colour, as of Clearneſſe, and Innocence; ſo, of Lenity, Kindneſſe, and of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>And, (which muſt not be paſſed over) both theſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, when actually upon his Throne, Seated there; not, in any poſture of haſte, as on any ſudden to paſſe ſentence, before due pawſing, examination, or conviction; Hee firſt ſits down, and ponders the whole cauſe; As much as this was intimated in the Lords proceeding with <hi>Sodom, Gen.</hi> 18.21. the enormities whereof, though they were exceeding clamorous, and cryed to heaven for judgment; yet before the execution of fire and brimſtome upon them, he is ſaid, firſt, to goe down, and ſee whether all things anſwered that loud and lewd report of their unnaturall and moſt prodigious crimes: <hi>I ſaw</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>a great while throne; Great,</hi> for Terror, and Severity; <hi>White,</hi> for Lenity, and Moderation; a <hi>Throne,</hi> for Counſel, and ſage Deliberation.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:34671:14"/>
            <p>And ſo I come to the next particular, which the Text in order preſents us with, and that is the Judge fitting on his throne, who is here ſaid to be God himſelf, ſet forth under expreſſions of Majeſtick terror, <hi>from whoſe face the earth and the heaven flee away, and there was found no place for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God himſelf then is the Judge, ſeated upon his throne; ſo is his ſtyle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. <hi>God the Judge of all,</hi> even Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; which howſoever diſtinguiſhed in regard of Perſonal ſubſiſtence, and peculiar appropriations of operations, yet are ſtill but One, and the ſame in Eſſence, and divine Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; even as if you take water, and ice, and ſnow, though in Apprehenſion diſtinct things, yet put together into one veſſell, and diſſolved, all prove but one water: or, as<note n="(r)" place="margin">Gregor. Nyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Catech. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> makes the obſervation, in <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 18.2, 3. who though, as it's ſaid, <hi>He ſaw three men from his tent dore,</hi> yet hee called all but <hi>[my] Lord,</hi> in the fingular; as for the device of the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> that theſe three Men were three Archangels, <hi>Michael,</hi> who foretold the birth of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Son; <hi>Raphael,</hi> who healed him of his wound received in his Circumciſion; and <hi>Gabriel,</hi> who reſcued <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom;</hi> this conceit we may reckon among thoſe which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>fooliſh and unlearned queſtions,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.23. the myſtery of the Text is to repreſent the Trinity of Perſons, in the Unity of the divine Eſſence: ſo <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.22. <hi>The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our Lawgiver, the Lord is our King,</hi> this three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold repetition of the word <hi>Jehovah,</hi> implyeth the myſtery of the Holy Trinity, as<note n="(s)" place="margin">Ioh. Gerard. loc. Com. tom. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> ſect. <hi>26.</hi> tract. de Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremojudicio.</note> 
               <hi>Gerard</hi> apprehends it: <hi>To the Father judgment is given, Pſal.</hi> 9.8. <hi>The Lord hath prepared his throne for judgment, and he ſhall judge the world in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe;</hi> &amp; Joh. 8.50. <hi>There is one that judgeth,</hi> ſaith Chriſt of his <hi>Father;</hi> compare we 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. To the <hi>Son</hi> it is aſcribed, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.42. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.8. to the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, Iſa.</hi> 4.4. called the <hi>Spirit of Judgment:</hi> The ground of this is that known Maxime in Divinity, <hi>Opera Trinitatis ad extra ſunt indiviſa,</hi> look as the Eſſence of the three Perſons is aequall, individed, and the ſame, ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34671:14"/>is the power, and work one, in relation to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>And yet, howſoever this be orthodox truth, that the whole Trinity doe judge, in regard of their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or conſubſtantiality, Authoritatively; nevertheleſſe, the whole execution of this Judgment, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in regard of Diſpenſation, is committed unto the <hi>Son;</hi> the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> judge, but by the <hi>Son;</hi> ſo <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. <hi>He hath appointed a day, in the which he will judge the world in righteouſneſſe, by that Man whom he hath ordained,</hi> So <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> in which reſpect, the Judgment Seat is ſaid to be Chriſt's, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.10. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. And this is alſo an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Creed.</p>
            <p>The reaſons of it are principally theſe two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, becauſe the proceedings of the laſt Judgement being to be Viſible, it ſeemed good to the bleſſed Trinity, to appoint the managing thereof to the man <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that ſo the Judge might be ſeen in Majeſty; hence it's ſaid, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.27. <hi>He hath given him Authority to [execute] judgment alſo, [becauſe] He is the Son of many</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as<note n="(t)" place="margin">Pelargus in lo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. <hi>62.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pelargus</hi> expounds it, that is, <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Humanity;</hi> for, this particle <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>becauſe,</hi> in this place, is not Aitiologicall, Cauſall, for the Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not the Cauſe, of which that Judiciary power doth depend; but it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Demonſtrative, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nature, in reſpect of which that power is ſaid to be communicated unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ſecond Perſon: Now, the <hi>Godhead</hi> being inviſible, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. &amp; 6.16. it is ſaid truly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.30. <hi>They ſhall [ſee] the Son of man coming in the clouds of Heaven, with power and great glory;</hi> and <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. <hi>They ſhall [looke] on him, whom they have pierced;</hi> ſo likewiſe <hi>Act.</hi> 1.11. <hi>This ſame Jeſus which is taken up from you into Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner, as you have [ſee] him goe into Heaven.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Secondly, becauſe it is a part of the recompenſe of his Humiliation, I am ſure an eſpeciall part of his Regall authority, by vertue whereof all the enemies of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34671:15"/>Kingdome ſhall be forced to ſubmit to the aequity of his Sentence, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.11. <hi>Every knee ſhall how to him,</hi> and <hi>at his Name, Phil.</hi> 2.10. that is, all Creatures ſhall yeeld him homage, and bee forced to acknowledge his power, ſcepter and ſoveraignty: The Apoſtles indeed, <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.28. are ſaid to judge the world, by their ſolid Doctrine, and eminent Example, convincing them of their error, and ungracious courſes; and all the Saints in generall like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. ſhall judge even the Angels; however, not by Originall, and Supreme authority; yet, as<note n="(v)" place="margin">Ephe. 2.6.</note> Aſſeſſors with the Lord Chriſt, as it were upon the ſame Bench, by approbation, applauding the<note n="(w)" place="margin">Rev. 19.1.</note> Juſtice of him, who being, as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſtyles him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. <hi>the Judge of all the earth,</hi> cannot but doe right.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Now, for the majeſty under which he is here deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, in theſe words; <hi>From whoſe face the earth and the Heaven flee away, and there was found no place for them;</hi> many are the conjectures for the ſenſe; ſome underſtanding it of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing, and utter annihilation of the whole frame of this preſent Univerſe, being totally diſſolved, and melted by the fire of Conflagration at that day: ſome moderne Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors incline to this, for that they read, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2. <hi>I ſaw a new Heaven, and a new Earth; for the firſt Heaven, and the firſt Earth were paſſed away, and there was no more Sea:</hi> though<note n="(x)" place="margin">S. Auguſt. de Civ. cap. <hi>14.</hi> &amp; <hi>16.</hi> Ambroſ. Primaſ. Bede, Arethas, Ribera, ad loc. P. Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard. l. <hi>4.</hi> Diſt. <hi>47.</hi> D.</note> others, with as much judgement, apprehend it only to be an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>mutation,</hi> or <hi>alteration,</hi> in reſpect of qualities, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſpecies, or corrupt form, not of the actuall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of their Eſſence, or Beeing; a change of them into a melioration, not an abolition by annihilation; and they expound it by that in the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.25, 26. <hi>Of old haſt thou laid the foundation of the earth, and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are the work of thy hands, they ſhall periſh, but thou ſhalt endure; yea, all of them ſhall wax old like a garment, as a veſture ſhalt thou change them, and they ſhall be changed: As a Veſture]</hi> Now, you know the ſubſtance of the Body may remain the ſame, though the Veſture that covers it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changed from an old [<note n="(*)" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> faſhion], to a new: Now as a Diamond is not ſo well cut as by a Diamond, no more is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34671:15"/>the Scripture interpreted comparably, as by it ſelf: And to the ſame purpoſe is that, we read in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13. where is mention made of <hi>new Heavers,</hi> and a <hi>new Earth,</hi> after thoſe that now are, verſ. 7. being reſerved unto fire, are purged by it: Which fire at the laſt day, as<note n="(z)" place="margin">Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. ad <hi>4</hi> ſent. D. <hi>48.</hi> qu. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bonaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Durand. in <hi>4.</hi> ſent. D. <hi>47.</hi> qu. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Durandus,</hi> and Schooltmen are of opinion, ſhall not, (even as the waters were not in the old deluge) be anew created, as a new materiall Element; But, it ſhall be only <hi>Ignitio quaedam elementi purgandi,</hi> A certain fiery in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation, even as iron is made hot by a vehement heat, not by receiving any new ſubſtantiall form of fire into its ſelf; By vertue of which Ignition, the old droſſe which ſin had contracted over the face of the Creation, ſhall be defaecated, and repurged, and a new, freſh face, or beauty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to it.</p>
            <p>And yet, notwithſtanding all this, under the favour of more deep judgements, me thinks, by this flying away of the Heaven and Earth from before the face of this great Judge, is, as by a Periphraſis expreſſed, in effect, no more but this; namely, how the whole Creation ſhall be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, after a ſort, and vaniſh, as it were, at the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Preſence, and clarity of the Lord Chriſt: They ſhall ſee the<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat 24.30.</hi> Bellarm. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi> de I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mag. <hi>ſo</hi> Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donat. Co<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el. a Lap.</note> ſign of the Son of man, by which the Papiſts generally underrſtand the enſign of the Croſſe, by which he got the victory over all his Enenties; others, ſome<note n="(*)" place="margin">See the ela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borate Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Leigh,</hi> a choice Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſt, of vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous learning, and of great induſtry, on Mat. 24.30.</note> bright ſignall teſtimony of his dreadfull, and majeſtick approach to judgement, when the powers of heaven ſhall be<note n="(c)" place="margin">See Heb. 12.26, 27.</note> ſhaken, the earth tremble, the mountains be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned:<note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 1.7.8.</note> the ſtarres ſhall fall from Heaven, though not really (for if one ſtarre be bigger then the whole globe of Earth, as Aſtronomers acquaint us, what ſhall receive them all, in their fall?) but ſeemingly, as it were frighted from their ſtations; and the Sun ſhall loſe its light, though not in regard of its innate Being, yet in regard of the more glorious ſplendor of Chriſts appearance; even as S. <hi>Paul</hi> comparing the Goſpell with the Law, the Spirit with the Letter, ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Even that which was made glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, bad no glory in this reſpect by reaſon of the glory that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth:</hi> In a word, as the Pſalmiſt hath it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.7. <hi>The
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34671:16"/>ſea ſhall roar, and the fulneſſe thereof, the world, and they that dwell therein, before the Lord, for he cometh to judge the earth; with righteouſneſſe ſhall he judge the world, and the people with equity;</hi> yea, and that impartially, even without reſpect of perſons.</p>
            <p>Which leads me to the next particular, that here the Text in order preſents us with, and that is the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the perſons, thus impartially to be arraigned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this formidable, and majeſtick Judge: and theſe are ſmall, and great; <hi>I ſaw the dead, ſmall and great ſtand before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Small and Great</hi>] that is, as well young, as old, as <hi>Ribera:</hi> poor and rich, ſo<note n="(d)" place="margin">Dionyſius Carthuſianus l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> de qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor Noviſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis.</note> 
               <hi>Dionyſius Carthuſianus,</hi> Kings and Caeſars, as well as Subjects, and Peſants; in which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, we may ſay as the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.1, 2. <hi>Hear this all ye People, give ear all ye Inhabitants of the world, both low and high, rich and poor together;</hi> even men of low degree, and men of high degree, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.9. all the Heathen round about, <hi>Joel</hi> 3.12. all nations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.32. All muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before the Judgement ſeat of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. Chriſtians and Pagans; yea, the righteous, as the wicked, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12. Whether<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Tim. 4, 1.</note> quick, that is, whom the laſt day ſhall finde alive, or by a<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.51.</note> change, aequivalently dead, and revived again; or elſe having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed been dead, are raiſed up again, even all the world, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.9.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Judicium faciet geſtorum quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuorum,</l>
               <l>Cuncta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cunctorum cunctis arcana patebunt.</l>
            </q>
            <p>There is no reſpect of perſons with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p>Some curioſities there are coyned in the Mint of quaint heads, (as they would be accounted) about this univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of appearance in Judgement: As, in what age, or ſtature, Infants, and others very young ſhall ariſe from the dead; and they have taken the boldneſſe to determine, that it ſhall be about that Age, wherein Chriſt was in his fulneſſe upon earth, to wit, about 33; miſapplying to this purpoſe that Text, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.13 <hi>They ſhall all come,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34671:16"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to the meaſure of the ſtature of the Fulneſſe of Chriſt;</hi> or <hi>of the Age</hi> (as the originall bears it) <hi>of the Fulneſſe of Chriſt;</hi> whereas that place (if in my poor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, I miſapprehend not) is more genuinely meant of that ſpirituall proficiency, which under the power of the Ordinance, by the work of the Miniſtery, muſt by be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers improved to the higheſt degree: Another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of the Pontificians is, that Infants dying unbaptized appear not in Judgement, and their fancy is thus drawn out; Then, there ſhall be made a diſtribution into Sheep, and Goats; but ſuch being unbaptized cannot be reckoned among the Sheep, by reaſon of their ſin origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, nor among the Goats, for the want of actuall ſin; whereas yet the Text ſaith, that S. <hi>John</hi> ſaw <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſmall and little,</hi> as well as <hi>great and growen:</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that opinion is founded on a falſe ſuppoſall, to wit, of the abſolute neceſſity of the work done in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; ſo, as if, without the externall application of the water in the Signe, there were an impoſſibility of ſharing in the thing fignified; againſt the orthodox Judgements of the Reformation, according to the Scriptures. Another tiffany diſpute is this, How <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.17. That the righteous, as well as the wicked ſhall be judged; whereas it is ſaid, that the Saints themſelves ſhall be Judges of the world, as ye heard but now? To which the Reſolution may be this, that the very Saints them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as well as others, ſhall in reſpect of<note n="(*)" place="margin">Gerard.</note> preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be firſt preſented before the Tribunall of Chriſt; but having received the<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> Declarative ſentence of their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, of <hi>Come ye Bleſſed,</hi> they then meet the Lord in the aire; partly, by the aſſiſtance (happily) of Angels, and partly, by the agility of their own glorifyed bodies, being caught up to be Aſſeſſors with Chriſt, in the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Clouds of his glorious appearance, as the Judge of all men, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>But to ſpeak my mind freely, I am, in ſuch<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi de re obſcuriſſima diſputatur, non adjuvantibus Divinarum Scripturarum certis, clariſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> documentis, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibere ſe debet Humana prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio, nihil faciens in alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram partem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinando. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Peccat. merit. cap. ult.</note> abſtruſe myſteries as theſe, of opinion, that it's ſafer to offend of too much modeſty (if at leaſt, that be an offence) then of too much audacity, and praeſumption to determine:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34671:17"/>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Quo modo at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> or dine il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud ſit ſuturum magis tunc do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebit [experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia] quam nunc valet conſequi ad perfectum Hominum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligentia. S. Auguſt. lib. <hi>20.</hi> de civ. Dei, cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> Experience muſt, and will be, in this, the ſureſt Umpire, in that great, and glorious Day of Revelation: In the mean time, in this grave aſſembly, I ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fine-ſpun opinions, as ornaments to be worn only in the ear; rather think it my duty to enforce the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of my Text; which is clearly, to convince us, that all, and every, <hi>ſmall and great,</hi> ſhall impartially, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons be preſented before this awfull, and majeſtick Judge of all the earth; For ſo ſaith expreſly S. <hi>John</hi> in the Text, <hi>I ſaw the dead ſmall and great ſtand before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which now brings me next in order to that part, which I ſtyled the Arraignment of all perſons, of what rank and condition ſoever they be, noted from this expreſſion, <hi>They ſtand before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, as the word imports, <hi>as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of God;</hi> ſo that, whatſoever cunning Artifice there may be, to contrive Maeanders, or crafty fetches of wit, or machinations to conceal the hidden and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den things of darkneſſe; ſaying with thoſe in the<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſal. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Pſalm: Tuſh, the Lord ſhall not ſee;</hi> yet then all thoſe pavilions, all thoſe mantles of Darkneſſe ſhall bee to no purpoſe at all, nor of any more advantage to hide them from the al-ſeeing eye of this piercing, ſoul-ſearching Judge, then were thoſe<note n="(l)" place="margin">Gen. 3.7.</note> fig-leaves to cover <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt nakedneſſe, or that buſh in Paradiſe, to ſhelter him from the voyce, or wrath of Heaven: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>], ſaith the great Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Wee muſt all appear,</hi> or <hi>[be made manifeſt]</hi> as the word imports, <hi>before the Judgment Seat of Chriſt:</hi> In this great Harveſt day of the Lord, the Angells, as Gods Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, ſhall from all the four corners of the world gather up all Nations, and then, as it is <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.32. <hi>Before him ſhall be gathered all Nations, all muſt come forth,</hi> as St. <hi>John</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.29. <hi>When the Lord cometh,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 5 <hi>he both will bring to light the hidden things of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and will make manifeſt the counſels of the hearts:</hi> And again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>God ſhall judge the [ſecrets] of men by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> neither is there any Creature, that is not manifeſt in his ſight, but all things are naked, and open unto the eyes of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34671:17"/>him, with whom we have to doe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'tis in that Text by a Metaphor borrowed from Anatomiſts, who, to diſcover how<note n="(*)" place="margin">Pſal. 139.15.</note> curiouſly the Lord had wrought all the parts of Nature within a man, are wont to diſſect him even from the neck, <hi>per ſpinam dorſi,</hi> down through the very chine bone, and ſo the very inmoſt cels, and cloſets, every nerve, and vein, and artery, and veſſell is diſcovered, and laid open to the eye, and view of the diſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: Even ſo is the whole man, in his cloſeſt thoughts, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and intentions to the Lord the Judge: and the extent of this reacheth as well to the good, as to the bad, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14.</p>
            <p>Godly men are, in this life, under a threefold cloud, hidden, <hi>Pſal</hi> 83.3. and as it were unobſerved, becauſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured: The firſt is a cloud of Hypocriſie: it's an old word, <hi>Mundus univerſus exercet Hiſtrioniam;</hi> as Players upon the Stage come on diſguiſed under the habits of ſeverall Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they being nothing leſſe indeed, then what they ſeem to be in ſhew; and yet, till they be all unmaſqued, are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for what they only ſeem to be; by which occaſion, tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell often paſſeth for ſilver, and copper for gold, Hypocriſie for ſincerity, a wooden leg with a ſilken ſtocking, a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill covered with ſnow, are taken for ſound, and fair, till the ſun diſcover the quite contrary: or, as <hi>Maginus</hi> writes, in his Geography, of the river Jordan, which ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth at the foot of the mountain <hi>Libanus</hi> from a double head, the one being called <hi>Jor,</hi> and the other <hi>Dan,</hi> which glideth along in a ſweet, and ſilver ſtream, pleaſant to behold, but it emptieth it ſelf at laſt, <hi>in mare mortuum,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dead ſea; ſo theſe hollow profeſſors ſeem to<note n="(m)" place="margin">Iſa. 12.3.</note> draw water, and to be refreſhed from the Word and Sacraments, as from the two ſprings of <hi>Jor</hi> and <hi>Dan,</hi> and ſwim along in a ſtream of complacency to all beholders, not to be detected till, in the upſhot, and<note n="(*)" place="margin">See 1 Cor. 4.5.</note> end of all, (which will be their tryall) they empty themſelves out into the dead ſea of Apoſtaſie: and indeed uſually it proves true, whoſoever begins in Hypocriſie ends in Apoſtaſie: But yet till the Scene is over, and the Act done, during the time of the ſtage, it had need be a Lyncean eye to diſcriminate a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34671:18"/>true <hi>Nathanael,</hi> an Iſraelite indeed, from an oppoſite in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe. And ſith it hath ſo pleaſed the Lord of the field to ſuffer tares to grow together with the wheat, untill the Harveſt, the nettle, and the myrtle, the hemlock, and the roſe in the ſame garden, good fiſh and bad to be in the ſame Net, clean and unclean beaſts in the ſame Arke, <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> and <hi>Simon Peter</hi> in the ſame Church among vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Profeſſors, till the laſt<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mat. 3 12.</note> fan make a finall<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat. 25.23.</note> ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the godly will be here under a cloud, by Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is a cloud of Sin and Corruption, which like a<note n="(*)" place="margin">Joſh. 15.63. &amp; 23.13.</note> Jebuſite in <hi>Canaan</hi> will not out of their coaſts, that Hydra of originall evill will ſtill be repullulating; as in the womb of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> ſo in the wils of the beſt men, Carnall <hi>Eſau's</hi> often<note n="(p)" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> ſtruggle with Spirituall <hi>Jacob's;</hi> and, to ſpeak with<note n="(q)" place="margin">Tertullian. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> contr. Nationes.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his <hi>African</hi> ſtyle, <hi>Caelum ipſum nulla ſerenitas tam colata purgat, ut non alicujus nubeculae flocculo reſignetur,</hi> In the cleareſt ſerenity of the Firmament, ſome ſpeckling cloud may be diſcovered, as a mole was in the very face of <hi>Venus,</hi> or a foyle nigh ſet to ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Diamond; ſome blots, oft-times, in the face of the Church, as in the face of the Moon, to which ſhe is reſembled, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10. Yea, many times, when we would wind up our thoughts to the ſweeteſt meditation upon God, they do like the pegs of an inſtrument, ſlip down between our fingers, and prove untunable; Now it falling out ſo, that the<note n="(r)" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> ſlips of the Saints, though but of infirmity, being more both watched, and obſerved, then their firmeſt ſtanding, theſe ſet them often under a cloud, and they become obſcured.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt is a cloud of ſorrowes, and afflictions, to which they are appointed, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.22 A Chriſtians life is not like the Hill <hi>Olympus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>wholly clear, without Clouds; Chriſtianus</hi> is <hi>quaſi Crucianus,</hi> as one ſaith, it comes from <hi>Crux,</hi> as well as <hi>Chriſtus;</hi> nor can there be a truer inſcription, wherewith to incircle ſo deſpiſed a coyn as the Church is, then that in <hi>Can.</hi> 2.2. <hi>As a Lilly among Thornes, ſo is my Love among the Daughters,</hi> ſure to be torn by Adverſity: ſhe is like to the buſh of <hi>Moſes,</hi> preſerved from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34671:18"/>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note> conſuming, yet ſeldome out of the flames of Tryall by ſufferings; or, as the Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> though ſaved from finking, yet toſſed in a ſea, and<note n="(t)" place="margin">Gen. 7.17.</note> upon the bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of ſorrow: and during that ſtate, ſhe is often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded under ſhowres, and ſtormes.</p>
            <p>But now, when the day ſhall come, wherein men make their generall appearance, before this great Tribunall, in the Text; then ſhall all theſe clouds be removed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.43. <hi>Then, ſhall the righteous ſhine forth as the Sun, in the Kingdome of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> They ſhall not only come [to] Judgement, but be able alſo to ſtand [in] Judgement; yea, <hi>to lift up their heads</hi> with joy, and with alacrity <hi>ſtand before the Sonne of man, Luk.</hi> 21.28, 36. But, as for the ungodly, it is not ſo with them, <hi>They ſhall not ſtand in the judgement, Pſal.</hi> 1.5. but, when the laſt ſhril Trump ſhall blow, and the Dead ariſe, they ſhall, though all in vain, endeavour to hide their heads for horrour, calling for rocks and mountains to<note n="(u)" place="margin">Rev. 6.16.</note> cover them from the preſence of the Judge, who then ſhall ſet all their ſins (though never ſo ſecret) in order<note n="(w)" place="margin">Pſal. 50.51.</note> before their faces; even then, when they ſhall be drag'd from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their graves, ſhackled in the chains of guilt, and ſo arraigned, and ſet to the Barre of Juſtice, <hi>to ſtand before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I paſſe from what I termed the Arraignment, to that, which in the order of Judicature, is called the Indictment, which here ſtands entred upon record, <hi>The Books were opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſaw the Dead, ſmall and great, ſtand before God, and the Books were opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I haſten.</p>
            <p>By theſe <hi>Books</hi> thus here, and in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. ſaid to be <hi>opened,</hi> we may not apprehend any<note n="(x)" place="margin">Si hic liber carnaliter co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitetur, quis ejus magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, aut lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitudinem va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leat aeſtimare? &amp;c. S. Auguſt. de Civ. Dei c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> materiall Volumes preſented before the Lord, with a Catalogue of the Names, or actions of all men to be Judged, as if the Lord did ſtand in need of any ſuch Information; <hi>Loe,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.5. <hi>Thou O Lord, haſt beſet me behind and before, ſearched me, and known my thoughts, words, and actions; Pſal.</hi> 11.4. <hi>The Lords Throne is in Heaven, his eyes behold, his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34671:19"/>eye-lids, try the children of men:</hi> to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Job</hi> 34.21.<note n="(y)" place="margin">Heſiod. lib <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the Poet hath it; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid an old Poet <hi>Philemon,</hi> mentioned by<note n="(z)" place="margin">Iuſtin. Martyr. lib. de M<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>narchia Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtin Martyr;</hi> the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> therefore called him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the inſpector of all things;</hi> and ſome Criticks in the <hi>Greek</hi> tongue are of an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifying <hi>God,</hi> is derived <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of a word which denoteth an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſall ſeeing,</hi> or behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of things: This ſearcher of all mens hearts doth alone<note n="(a)" place="margin">Hooker l. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>82.</hi> Eccleſ. Polit.</note> Intuitively know who are his, ſaith learned <hi>Hooker; The Lord Chriſt knoweth all things,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, Job.</hi> 21.17. &amp; 2.25. to the ſame purpoſe are thoſe many other Texts, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. &amp; 23.24. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.39. <hi>Pſal</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Cor &amp; renes in occulto latitant: ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur ergo Deum abſcondita co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitationum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum ſcire.</note> 7.9. <hi>Job</hi> 42.2, 3. But theſe Books are only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, aſcribed to the Lord, by way of dignation, or gracious condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, God ſpeaking after the manner of men, that men might the better conceive of the things of God; and the meaning of them is, that all things thought, or ſaid, or done by men, ſtand all as it were upon record, and are all exactly remembred by the Lord, and brought likewiſe afreſh unto the memories of all men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. <hi>Setting them all in order before their eyes;</hi> ſo that <hi>Auſtin</hi> thinks thereby, <hi>quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam vis eſt intelligenda divina,</hi> a certain power of God is underſtood, by means, or by virtue whereof all the deeds of men are in a wonderfull ſerenity recalled to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, <hi>ut accuſet, vel excuſet ſcientia conſcientiam,</hi> that, according as they prove to be, ſcience may either accuſe, or elſe excuſe conſcience: And they are all called <hi>Books,</hi> in the plurall number, not, in reſpect of the mind, or of the knowledge of God, which is a moſt pure, and ſimple act; but, in reſpect of the variety of the objects, or diverſity of the things therein inſcribed.</p>
            <p>And yet Divines both for order, and diſtinction ſake, have given ſeverall Titles to theſe my ſticall, and ſpirituall <hi>Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The firſt is the <hi>Book of Nature,</hi> or <hi>of Providence,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.16. <hi>In thy Book are all my members written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond is of <hi>Gods Remembrance, Mal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 56.8.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:34671:19"/>
            <p n="3">3. The Book of <hi>Mans Conſcience,</hi> which is <hi>Volumen grande,</hi> as one calleth it, a large volume, wherein all things are written by the ſtyle of Verity, and for the amending of which Book all other Books were invented; ſo<note n="(c)" place="margin">S. Ambroſ. ad Pſal. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> What are theſe <hi>Books opened,</hi> ſaith hee, but Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? <hi>Non atramento ſcripti, ſed veſtigiis delictorum, &amp; flagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum inquinamento?</hi> not written with Inke, but ſtamped with the Impreſſion of black Sinnes, and moſt ugly Offences.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Book of <hi>Life, Phil.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.5. by which is underſtood <hi>Catalogus Savandorum,</hi> the Catalogue of the Elect, whom God in Chriſt hath choſen from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity unto Salvation; who though they now be unknown, yet ſhall then be more manifeſtly declared.</p>
            <p n="5">5. To which ſome adde, fiftly, the Books of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> the <hi>Two Teſtaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All of theſe Books ſhall be, perhaps, at that day brought forth, bound up together in one volume, which being unclaſped ſhall diſcover all matters, how they have been tranſacted, managed and done in the body, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.25, 26. Some mens ſins are open before-hand, going before to Judgment, and ſome men they follow after; likewiſe alſo the good works of ſome are manifeſt before-hand, and they that are otherwiſe cannot be hid; that is, ſome evil deeds are puniſhed in this world, to give notice that there is an eye of Providence that obſerves them here; and ſome likewiſe are reſerved for hereafter, to ſhew that there is a Judgment to come: The good works likewiſe of ſome follow them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. that is, the reward of their good works ſhall be imparted hereafter: In ſumme, The generall reſolve in this matter is, that by theſe <hi>Books opened</hi> are mainly meant the Conſciences of all men; the office of which is to<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rom. 2.14, 15.</note> accuſe, or to excuſe, according to the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Field</hi> l. 4. c. 33. of the Church.</note> privity that the ſoul hath to things good or ill, known to none, but to God, and it ſelf: the Conſcience being, as it were, Gods Regiſter Book, wherein all the ſins of the Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and Unregenerate, or Caſtawayes, with all their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall circumſtances of aggravation, are kept under their guilt uncancelled, unſtruck-out: It's true indeed, that <hi>Actus
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34671:20"/>tranſit,</hi> but <hi>Reatus permanet,</hi> the act of Sin was tranſient, and momentany, not ſo the guilt; no, that is written with a<note n="(f)" place="margin">Jer. 17.1.</note> pen of Iron, and with the point of a Diamond, and graven (as it were in characters indeleble) upon the table of their heart, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.1. And this is the Act of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to be its own Teſtimony, yea, a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes againſt it ſelf: Hence was that ſaying of<note n="(g)" place="margin">Lactant. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Quid prodeſt non habere Conſcium, habenti Conſcientiam?</hi> It is a true word of the Apoſtle, <hi>God is greater then our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.20. and ſurely none but He: Yet under that great God, the Supreme power on earth, (within a man) is the Conſcience: In this Microcoſme of Man, (ſaith a devout<note n="(h)" place="margin">B. H. Soliq. 51. edit. 1651.</note> Divine) there is a Court of Judicature erected, wherein, next under God, the Conſcience ſits as the Chief Juſtice, from which there is no appeal; if that condemne us, or our actions, in vain ſhall all the world beſides acquit us, and if that clear us, all other doom on earth is frivolous, and ineffectuall: O the agonies of a guilty boſome unacquitted within it ſelf! like <hi>Paſhur,</hi> it's a<note n="(i)" place="margin">Jer. 20.4. &amp; Pſal. 73.19.</note> terror to it ſelf: yea, very <hi>Ethniques</hi> many experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſometimes the ſtroke but of Naturall Conſcience, were wont to ſet it forth by their <hi>Erinnes,</hi> or Helliſh Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries purſuing the flagitious with flaming firebrands, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting with all extremity; the noyſe of a leaf<note n="(k)" place="margin">Lev. 26.36.</note> ſhaken ſtartles them, being afraid, alas! where no feare is; <hi>For Wickedneſſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> ch. 17.11.) <hi>condemned by her own witneſſe is very timorous, and being preſſed with Conſcience, alwaies forecaſteth grievous things, that fear being nothing elſe but a betraying of the ſuccours, which Reaſon offereth:</hi> Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe can never think it ſelf ſecure; if there were no Fiends to torment it, like a Boſome-devil, it would like trembling<note n="(l)" place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> and as <hi>Cain</hi> the<note n="(m)" place="margin">Gen. 4.15.</note> marked vagabond, ever torture it ſelf; <hi>There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked, Iſa.</hi> 57.21. <hi>Aut ſi pax, bello pax ea dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior;</hi> yea, <hi>the wicked are like the troubled Sea, when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up mire, and dirt:</hi> all the winds in the world, from without, cannot make a mountain ſhake, but the impriſoned vapors that are within: Truly ſpake one, once, <hi>All the world for a clear Conſcience!</hi> wonder we
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34671:20"/>at the wiſh? <hi>A wounded Spirit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, who can bear? Prov.</hi> 18.14. On the other ſide again; I ſay, on the other ſide, (For, we<note n="(n)" place="margin">Mar. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>Fiſhers of men</hi> muſt have our Cork, as well as our Lead; our Cork, to boye up penitent ſoules from finking in the mighty waters of Deſpair, as well as our Lead to ſink them into hell, who perſevere incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible) O the tranquillity of a ſpotleſſe breaſt! when theſe <hi>Books are opened,</hi> and the characters of guilt are found to bee expunged, no ſin at all<note n="(o)" place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.</note> imputed to ſo bleſſed a ſoul: Beloved Chriſtians, there is but one remedy of the forementioned malady, but one principall Receipt to eat out, or to fret away that canker which ſin hath brought into the ſpirit, or rather to waſh away the ſpots which<note n="(p)" place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> defile the Conſcience, and that is in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. the blood of ſprinkling, even the precious blood of the Lamb<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19.</note> without ſpot, even <hi>the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, which cleanſeth from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. even <hi>that blood which</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note> 
               <hi>ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth better things then the blood of</hi> Abel, the one cryed to Heaven for Judgment, but the Lord Chriſt's for Mercy; one line, or as it were but one red ſtrake of his bloud drawn through that Book, cleareth and acquitteth all: Let ſuch an one be arraigned, let him be indicted, yea, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by the <hi>grand Accuſer of the Brethren, Rev.</hi> 12.10. accuſed before God, day and night; yet bring him to the Teſt, and the proofe will bee all, <hi>According to the Evidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed in order, to the next particular, which after the Indictment, I ſtyled the Evidence, the things written in the Books; <hi>The Dead were judged out of thoſe things which were written in the Books.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all regular, or legall Judicatures, before the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, there goes Conviction, and that grounded upon ſome clear Evidence, according to ſome rule of Law, which directs, and orders Juſtice in that reſpect: Now, that which directs the buſineſſe in the Text, is no other then the Word of God, the obſervation, or the violation of the commands whereof, clears, or charges the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to receive the Sentence of Abſolution, or of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, according to the Evidence: <hi>Doe not thinke,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:34671:21"/>ſaith our Saviour, (the Judge in my Text) <hi>that I will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe you to the Father, there is one that accuſeth you, even</hi> Moſes, <hi>in whom yee truſt, Joh</hi> 5.45. by <hi>Moes</hi> hee meanes the Writings of <hi>Moſes, ver.</hi> 47. Again, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.48. <hi>Hee that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my words; hath one what judgeth him, the Word that I have ſpoken, the ſam ſhall judge him at the laſt day:</hi> Compare <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.12. and it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid to be Organically, or Inſtrumentally, <hi>A diſcerner ef the thoughts, and of the intents of the heart, Heb.</hi> 4.12. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16. <hi>God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpell,</hi> that is, in a generall acception of the Word, according to the whole ſyſteme of Doctrine preached by Chriſt, his Prophets, and Apoſtles, epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed into the Goſpel: The righteous ſhall be judged, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, (ſaith<note n="(s)" place="margin">Gerard. ſect. <hi>70.</hi> ubi ſupra.</note> one) according to the termes of the Goſpel, and bee abſolved; the wicked, out of the Law, (colluſtrated by the light of the Goſpel) thereby being convinced of ſin and infidelity, and be condemned; and indeed, Divines are of opinion, that there ſhall not bee in the laſt day any other <hi>norma,</hi> or rule to order, or to direct the Judgement, then what is already paſſed before in the Miniſtry of the Word: The Conſcience is<note n="(t)" place="margin">Joh. 10.23. Matth. 18.18</note> bound or looſed Before, as the Keyes are rightly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: The Sentence of the Judge at the laſt day, is not a new making of Salvation, or Damnation; but onely a ſolemne, and publick teſtification, propalation, or defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive ratihabition of what was before paſſed in the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Judgment by the Word, or inſtantly after Death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. Wherefore the laſt day is ſtyled the <hi>[Revelation]</hi> namely, publick, <hi>of the righteous judgement of God,</hi> that is, of that particular, righteous Judgement, paſſed upon diſcuſſion, between God and the Conſcience, before, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. thus we read the ſentence of the word to be this, <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and anguiſh upon every ſoule of man that doth evill, but glory, honor, and peace to every one that worketh good, Rom.</hi> 2.9, 10. &amp; 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6, 7. all which, in the aequivalent, is declared, and more openly ratified in the <hi>Come yee Bleſſed;</hi> and in the <hi>Goe yee Curſed,</hi> at the laſt day; each of theſe, according to the Evidence, <hi>out of what is written in the Bookes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:34671:21"/>
            <p>Upon this occaſion, I have read of one much retired, and given to devotion, who being asked, what book he was moſt of all ſeen in, and accuſtomed to read, made anſwer, That he read eſpecially one, and that was a book of three leaves, a red leaſe, a black leaſe, and a white leafe; in the red leaſe he read the Paſſion of Chriſt; in the black leaſe, the Puniſhment of the Damned; and in the white leaſe, the joyes of the Bleſſed; by peruſall, and meditation of which three leaves, he more profited, then if he had evolved all the Philoſophers in the world.</p>
            <p>And thus, at length, we are come to the Judgment, or Sentence-giving it ſelf, in the next words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Dead were judged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Doctrine of <hi>the Judgment to come</hi> was never more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be preached then now among us, upon whom the<note n="(v)" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> ends of the world are come; all the lees and dregs of former times ſeeming to be about to ſettle, in this laſt, and corrupt age; wherein, alas! whileſt Atheiſme, like the<note n="(w)" place="margin">Jon. 4.7.</note> worm in <hi>Jonah</hi>'s gourd, hath eaten out the ſap of Religion, and almoſt damp'd the very life, and power of godlineſſe, wee meet with thoſe<note n="(x)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>from</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quod ſignificat ludo pueriliter <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, veluti puer, puerorum more; <hi>ſuch as make children play of the Terrors of the Lord.</hi> M. L.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe ſcoffers, of whom S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> makes mention, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3, 4. alſo <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 18. <hi>walking after their own luſts, and ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> vainly, and ſcoffingly putting<note n="(y)" place="margin">Jam. 1.22. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> paralogiſmes, or deceivings upon themſelves, ſophiſtically reaſoning from the delay of the time to a Nullity of the thing it ſelfe, and <hi>becauſe Sentence is not executed ſpeedily againſt their evill works, therefore, as Solomon</hi> long agoe obſerved, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.11. <hi>the heart of the ſons of men are fully ſet in them to doe evill;</hi> and ſo believe the Doctrine of <hi>the Judgment to come</hi> to be but fabulous, together with the torments of Hell that follow after it, upon all ſuch mockers: To whom I ſhall onely now ſay thus much, <hi>Vae quibus haec experienda ſunt prius, quam credenda,</hi> as<note n="(z)" place="margin">Granatenſe tom. <hi>2.</hi> Conc. d. Temp. Conc. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Granatenſis</hi> expreſſeth it, Woe bee to thoſe beſotted, and impenitent miſcreants, whoſe ſad experience may anticipate their Credulity in this, and prevent their Faith! O how well had <hi>Felix</hi> (that corrupt Governor) anſwered his name, and been happy, if as the reaſoning about this truth made his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34671:22"/>to tremble, he had inſtantly reformed his practice, and ſhun'd the danger of it, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.25.</p>
            <p>But, for the atteſtation of this Doctrine, the Firmament is not more beſpangled with ſtarres, then the Scriptures are ſtored throughout with proofes thereof: <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam</hi> propheſied hereof, ſaith <hi>Jude, v.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>Behold, the Lord cometh with Ten thouſand of his Saints, to execute Judgement upon all, both for their deeds and ſpeeches:</hi> From whence St. <hi>Jude</hi> had that Propheſie, whether by undoubted tradition, as <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to have received the names of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres,</hi> the Magicians that withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. or by ſome<note n="(a)" place="margin">Vid. Scalig. in notis ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. p. <hi>244.</hi> &amp;c.</note> book written of the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Enoch,</hi> extant in that Apoſtles dayes, but ſince intercepted by time; (though I am praeciſely of<note n="(b)" place="margin">S. Auguſt. lib. <hi>18.</hi> de Civ. Dei, cap. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>'s opinion, that however ſome records might be loſt, which did <hi>pertinere ad ubertatem Cognitionis,</hi> appertain to the plenty of Knowledge; yet the Church hath been ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a Keeper of the ſacred Canon, that nothing is eſcaped her cuſtody, which doth belong <hi>ad Authoritatem Religionis,</hi> to the Authority of Religion) It's moſt likely S. <hi>Jude</hi> might receive it, by Apoſtolicall and immediate Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſome praeludiums whereof were ſeen in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the old world by<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gen. 7. 2 Pet. 3.6.</note> Water, and of the Cities of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> by<note n="(d)" place="margin">Gen. 19. 2 Pet. 2.6. &amp; S. Jud. ver. 7.</note> Fire; the two colours in the Rainbow figure it; the caerulean colour minds us of the watery Deluge paſt, and the flame colour, of the<note n="(e)" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.10.</note> fiery Conflagration to come.</p>
            <p>It would be a large, if not a tedious taske for mee to enumerate all thoſe Texts, which in <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and almoſt in each page of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment make mention hereof, and prove the Doctrine: Two places (which I have alſo named already) may be in ſtead of all, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. and the manner of it is expreſſed in the 24, and 25. Chapters of S. <hi>Matthew:</hi> But yet to ſay ſomething of it. 1. This may be proved from what hath been already ſeen in thoſe particular Judgments inflicted, in the courſe of Gods providence upon impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſinners inwardly, and outwardly, as upon <hi>Cain, Ahitophel, Judas, Herod,</hi> whom God was pleaſed to make
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34671:22"/>viſible Examples here, and thereby alſo to give intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what, in the laſt day of wrath, is like to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on ſuch, as committing like ſins are [reſerved] with the apoſtate and damned Angels to the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee puniſhed, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. 2. Beſides this, the juſtice of God, and the truth of his promiſe, in regard of the righteous requires it, whoſe afflicted eſtate in this life ſhall be recompenſed with a glorious one hereafter, and all their perſecutors have ſhame and conſuſion poured upon their faces forever, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5. 3. That there may bee a publick acknowledgment of the Lord Chriſts Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, purchaſed by his paſſion to himſelfe, over men, and Angels, ſo that every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue confeſſe unto him, and own his Soveraign power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.9, 10, 11. 4. Equity requires it, that though the ſoule and body be ſeparated in death, yet having ſinned or obeyed together, they ſhould accordingly be tormented or rejoyce together unto all eternity. In a word, ſome of the wiſer Heathen have diſcourſed of a future reward, upon tryal of mens actions, after death, making mention of <hi>Pluto, Minos, Rhadamanthus,</hi> &amp;c. as grim Judges, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the flakes of <hi>Aetna,</hi> to ſmel of the ſulphur of Hell: and moreover, what they alſo ſpeak of the <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields, implies an apprehenſion of ſome future eſtate of Happineſſe in another world. What need I adde more to this proof, ſith it is an expreſſe Article of our Creed, that Chriſt ſhall come again to judge the quick and the dead? proved alſo, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4, 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2.</p>
            <p>Now, (which I thought not amiſſe to mention, on this occaſion) howſoever our Saviour interdicted his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples the curious in quiſition after the times, and ſeaſons, <hi>Act.</hi> 1.7. ſith the Father hath put [that] in his own power; yet there have been found ſome, in all ages, very adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous, who (as<note n="(f)" place="margin">Bullinger lib. <hi>2.</hi> adverſ. Anabap. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bullinger</hi> writes of ſome Enthuſiaſts) have preſumed to define a ſet time for this generall Aſſiſes: though the Scripture indeed mention a ſet day determined by God for the ſame, as <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. and as St. <hi>John</hi> acquaints us, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. that, as there is <hi>Dies Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica,</hi> the Lords day; ſo St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.2. that there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34671:23"/>is <hi>Die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Domini,</hi> the day of the Lord, or the day of God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12. In the one, it is for us to give him, here, the Glory of his Publick ſervice; in the other, himſelf will give us that beleeve, then, and there, his Glory for our reward. Though this be ſaid in the generall, yet of the very Day, and<note n="(g)" place="margin">Mar. 13.32.</note> Hour before-hand, no man, no not the Son of man (as man) himſelf knoweth, at leaſt, thinks it not fit to acquaint us with ſo much.</p>
            <p>There is, as<note n="(b)" place="margin">Pet. Galatin. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Petrus Galatinus</hi> well ſtyleth it, a Thal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudiſticall tradition, but no true Propheticall prediction, (and yet it is mentioned almoſt by all, who treat on this ſubject) of one <hi>Elias,</hi> who undertook to foretell that the world ſhould laſt juſt 6000 years, 2000 before the giving of the Law, 2000 under the Law, and 2000 under the Goſpel; gathering it, they ſay, from <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 90.4. &amp; from <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. that <hi>a thouſand years with the Lord are but as one day, and one day as a thouſand years,</hi> and ſo allowing one day of the week for a thouſand years, by way of a reſembling computation, the time is made up; and the ſeventh day, as it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a day of a Spirituall (but of a Temporary) reſt, ſo then it ſhould be an everlaſting and glorious reſt to all true Belcevers: and the ſame, ſay men of that apprehenſion, was after a ſort preſigured in the Tranſlation of <hi>Enoch;</hi> for the ſix perſons, who were before him dying after the uſuall manner of dying, <hi>Enoch</hi> being the ſeventh, as S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, dyed not after the ordinary way, but was tranſlated, as it were in a figure hereof, extraordinarily, by God himſelfe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.24.</p>
            <p>Thus have theſe men ſpunne a thread upon the wheel of their owne imaginations, not uttered an opinion upon ſufficient warrant from Gods Word: for this cannot bee proved to bee the Propheſie of<note n="*" place="margin">1 King. 17.1.</note> 
               <hi>Elijah</hi> the <hi>Tiſhbite,</hi> who propheſied under King <hi>Ahab,</hi> about the Three thouſand and fortyeth yeare of the World, and Nine hundred and odde yeares before Chriſt, as ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Gerard. ubi ſupra, tom. <hi>9.</hi> ſect. <hi>77.</hi> ca. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Chronologers compute it; but of one <hi>Elias,</hi> a Jewiſh <hi>Rabbi,</hi> about ſome Two hundred years before Chriſt: But (by the way a little) if this conceit ſhould be Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick, and hold right, then that other opinion of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34671:23"/>
               <hi>Chiliaſts,</hi> or <hi>Millenaries,</hi> firſt mentioned by one<note n="*" place="margin">Euſcb. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Eccleſiaſt. Hiſt. cap uli. Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. Hiſt. c. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; Hieronym, in Catalogo Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. in vita Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piae. vid. Ribc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram Comment. in Apocal. c. <hi>20.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>380, 381.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Papias</hi> of <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> (as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> reports it) but much exploded in that age, yet of late taken up again by many, who have found more leiſure to raiſe doubts, then (under that odde affectation of Singularity) declared any ſatisfactory re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves unto them hereabout; that opinion I ſay, muſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: They pretend, that Chriſt ſhall come perſonally, and viſibly to reign a thouſand years upon earth, before the Day of the laſt generall Judgement: and all thoſe who dyed Patriarchs, or Prophets, or Apoſtles, Martyrs, or Confeſſors, or any eminent Saints, and Iſraelites, and Chriſtians<note n="(i)" place="margin">Joh. 1.47.</note> indeed, ſhall then be raiſed up from the dead to reign with him; and this they think is underſtood by the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. Thus an Error; or, in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt expreſſion, a Miſtake confutes a Praeſumption; for if Chriſt muſt reign a thouſand years viſibly upon earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of Judgement, and that firſt Reſurrection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not yet paſt, then, of neceſſity, the world muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue above 6000 years, for that we are now within 400 years expiration of thoſe 6000, and yet that bodily Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection is not come to paſſe.</p>
            <p>But, as to this latter opinion, beſides the known maxime in Divinity, <hi>Scriptura ſymbolica non eſt argumentativa;</hi> many ſound, orthodox Divines do conceive it to have in it too worldly, and too carnall an apprehenſion of the Nature of Chriſts Kingdome, ſith Himſelf hath ſaid it, that it was not of this world, <hi>Job.</hi> 18.36. in the outward<note n="(k)" place="margin">Act. 25.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> phantaſies and pomp thereof; but Chriſts Kingdome is within, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. in the inner man, ſpirituall and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall: And it is no new thing in the Scriptures to call our New birth in grace a Reſurrection, by ariſing ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the graves of our Naturall corruptions to a life of Holineſſe, even ſo it's underſtood, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1. Beſides, this were to make ſome addition to the Articles of our Creed, which neither mentions, nor implies three viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Comings of the Lord Chriſt; but only two, the one at his firſt appearance in the Fleſh to be Judged, and the other in Glory to Judge the world; even ſo the Holy Ghoſt expreſly by his Divine Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.18. <hi>He
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34671:24"/>ſhall to them that look for him appear</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>[the ſecond] time, without ſin, unto ſalvation:</hi> Chriſt comes but<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>D.</hi> Taylor.</note> twice Corporally, once to merit ſalvation, and again, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it.</p>
            <p>But I muſt contract this diſcourſe, and all I have to adde more under this Head is a double adviſe; The one, not to ſearch beyond a praecept after a Revelation unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, <hi>Noluit Deus prsdicari, quod videbat non utiliter ſeiri,</hi> ſaith<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>80.</hi> ad Helychaum.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> God would not have it known, beeauſe He ſaw it more profitable unknown: <hi>Neo tamen negatum eſt ad Detrimentum, quod ignoratum tribuit inerementum,</hi> as<note n="(n)" place="margin">Hilar. l. <hi>9</hi> de Trin.</note> 
               <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary:</hi> If God had foreſeen it advantageous for us, He would undoubtedly have revealed it unto us, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. But this He hath aſſured us of, that there is ſuch a day, and that it ſhall come <hi>as a thief in the night,</hi> ſuddenly, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. and S. <hi>James</hi> is expreſſe, chap. 5.8, 9. <hi>That the coming of the Lord draweth nigh,</hi> and (in moſt of the<note n="*" place="margin">Read Mat. 24 &amp; 2 Theſſ. 2 3.</note> praecurſory ſignes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) it's evident, that the Judge ſtandeth before the door, as it were, now ready to ſound the laſt Trump, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning all to the laſt generall Tribunall. Well then, what others give to a curious indagation of the time, let us (by caſting off thoughts of ſecurity) beſtow upon a ſerious, and hourly praeparation againſt that time, and hour, whenſoever it ſhall be, or how long ſoever that day ſhall continue, (which ſome have alſo unſatisfactori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if not praeſumptuouſly diſcourſed upon) or whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it ſhall be, whether in the vale of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> or in the Centre of the earth; let us, I ſay, leaving theſe unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> ſecret things to God, get into the Arke before the floud come, that we may be ſafe, when it doth come: <hi>Praeveniendus eſt Dies, qui praevenire conſuevit,</hi> ſaith a Father in a kinde of Prophecy, praevent that day by a ſedulous<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.12.</note> expectation, which may otherwiſe praevent us, and come upon us as at<note n="(p)" place="margin">Luk 21.34.</note> unawares,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Latet ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Dies, ut ch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerventur omnes Dies. S. Auguſt. l. <hi>50.</hi> Hom. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> thinking every day to be it. The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a Proverb, <hi>Qui colligit in veſpere ſabbati veſcetur in Sabbato,</hi> Who ſo gathers his Manna be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sabbath come, in the Eve, ſhall be fed with the ſame Manna, in the morrow, when the Sabbath is come: to which purpoſe give me leave I beſeech you, to offer to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34671:24"/>your conſiderations a<note n="(r)" place="margin">Vide li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum, cui Titu. lus eſt Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orium vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, a quodam no nine Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero conſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſub. <hi>41.6.</hi>
               </note> ſtory of a religious King, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of <hi>Hungaria,</hi> who took a reſolution to retire him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and ſo to take an exact ſurvey of himſelf, and of his actions, how he ſhould give up the laſt<note n="(s)" place="margin">Luk. 16.2.</note> account of himſelf, and of his great ſtewardſhip, both as a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and as a King, in that<note n="(t)" place="margin">Act. 2.20. Rev. 6 17.</note> great day, when after that generall Audit, he muſt be no longer Steward: The Nobles about his Court<note n="(u)" place="margin">Amos 6.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>chanting it to the noyſe of the violl, drinking wine in bowls, inventing to themſelves inſtrumen's of muſick, anoynting themſelves with the chief oyntments, and ſtretching themſelves upon Ivory couches,</hi> theſe put far from them the thought of this great day: (in like ſort as many of our ſupine Chriſtians every where, who have it often in their lips, upon any miſ-accident, Alas! they thought no more of it, then of their Dying Day; no nor or Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day neither; an ill-beſeeming expreſſion!) I ſay theſe jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viall gallants about the Court would needs by a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inſtigation ſtirre up the Duke the Kings brother to adventure to the Kings cloſet, to interrupt, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the ſullen fits of his melancholy, to perſwade him to minde his greatneſſe, to take the liberty of his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and forget ſorrowes: To this adviſe the King, for that inſtant, makes him no returns of anſwer, or of reply: but ſoon after makes an edict, and gives it abroad, that at whoſe door a Trumpet ſhould ſound, that man ſhould immediately be put to death: accordingly it ſounded at his Brothers lodgings, and the Serjeants apprehend him for execution; at which unexpected ſurpriſall being ſtartled, he makes his way to the King, becomes proſtrate at his feet, implores pardon, and mercy: under that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and poſture, then, (and not till then) the King ſpeaks to him, and ſaid, Ah my brother, are you ſo afraid of my Trumpet, who can but<note n="(w)" place="margin">Luk. 12.4.</note> take the body, or afflict the outward man; and ſhall not I tremble, and be afraid under the apprehenſion of that great Day, and of that dreadfull Tribunall of the ſupreme Potentate, <hi>the Lord of Lords, and the</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>King of Kings,</hi> when I ſhall be ſummoned thither by the laſt, and terrible<note n="(y)" place="margin">Theſſ. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Trumpe of the Archangell?</hi> Which ſaying was enough to have appalled his ranting
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34671:25"/>brother, yea to have put bowels into a rock, and have taught marble the art of relenting: I preſume the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to be eaſie: Wherefore, to end this part, it ſhall be not my admonition only, but my prayer alſo, that every one of us may alwayes bear in remembrance that not more known, then ſerious ſaying of S. <hi>Hiecome, Sive comedam, ſivebibam, ſive aliud quid agam, ſemper videtur tuba illa terribilis inſonare auribus meis, Surgite mortui, &amp; venite ad judicium,</hi> that is, Whether I eat, or drink, or whatſoever elſe I am about, me thinks that terrible Trumpet ſoundeth this ſaying in mine ears, <hi>Ariſe ye Dead, and come to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> which the learned<note n="(z)" place="margin">Voſſius diſputat. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. p. <hi>234</hi> edit. <hi>1628.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Voſſius</hi> hath, for memory ſake, turned into this Diſtich,
<q>
                  <l>Seu vigilo intentus ſtudiis, ſeu dormio, ſemper</l>
                  <l>Judicis extremi neſtras Tuba perſonat aures.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, at length, I am come to the laſt obſervable (at leaſt according to my diviſion) in this Text, and that is the Regulation of the finall ſentence it ſelf, whether of Abſolution, or of Condemnation; and this is expreſſed in the laſt words, <hi>According to their Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Quaere here is, whether Thoughts; and Words, and Omiſſions come not into account with the Lord, at the laſt Day? The Quaeſtion is out of quaeſtion, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly they ſhall all, however the denomination here be given to the more noted part: For the Thoughts it's clear, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. For the Words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.36. S. <hi>Jud.</hi> v. 14. For ſins of Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion it's evident from the form of the ſentence, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.42, &amp;c. <hi>You did not feed me, &amp;c.</hi> And for all other Works, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Even for whatſoever men have done in the Body:</hi> yet with this difference or oddes, to the godly, and to the wicked; to the godly it ſhall be <hi>ſecundum, non propter opera;</hi> not [for] their Works, as if the merit of them did deſerve a recompence of bliſſe, as a meritorious cauſe of ſalvation; for all [that] merit, is in Chriſt their Head, and mediator: and indeed, of all their moſt accompliſhed <hi>works</hi> of the greateſt Saints it may be ſaid, as <hi>Andrew</hi> did of the five Loaves, and two Fiſhes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Alas! Lord,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:34671:25"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh. 6 9. It was the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of</hi> Luther, Cave non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn a peccatis, ſed etiam a bo nis operibus. <hi>ſee Iſa. 64 6.</hi> Vae etiam lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabili juſtitiae lominum, ſi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mota iniſericer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia diſcutins eam, S. Auſtin.</note> 
               <hi>what are theſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> if laid in the ballance they would be found too lighty and thy Juſtice would infinitely praepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate; but Chriſt with the<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rev. 8.3.</note> incenſe of his merits hath perfumed the performances of the Saints unto an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation with God: the faith of the Righteous layes them as <hi>John</hi> in the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Joh. 13 23</note> boſome of Chriſt, and their good Works as S.<note n="(d)" place="margin">Mat. 26.58.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> follow<note n="(e)" place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> after them, as the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and manifeſtation of their Faith: But with the wicked, and impenitent reprobate the caſe is otherwiſe, becauſe the ſentence is pronounced upon them, <hi>propter opera,</hi> for their wicked, and ſinfull Works. Nor will this ſeem ſtrange, if we ſhall conſider what it is; that makes ſins culpable of damnation; what our weak ſervices ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of heavenly glory: we ſhall diſcover great oddes, mens ſins are culpable of death by their own Nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing committed againſt an endleſſe Majeſty, that cannot be ſatisfied but by a puniſhment commen ſurate and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal to his infinite Juſtice: but good Works become capable of their reward, 1 By the graoious promiſe of God, (<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendo ſe fecit debitorom,</hi> ſaith<note n="(f)" place="margin">Auguſ. de verbu Apoſt. ſer. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi>) who by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe only hath made himſelf a debtor. 2 By the merit of Chriſt, that hath purchaſed unto us a cover of their blemiſhes, and that they might be capable of aeternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Now, for the ſins of the obſtinate, incorrigible, and impenitent, the Lord hath received no ſatisfaction in the bloud of Chriſt, which they<note n="(g)" place="margin">Heb. 10.29.</note> trampled under feet; ſo that they lye ſtill under the guilt of all their ſins, and of all the ſeverall aggravatlons of the ſame, together with all the wrath, and formidable curſes, which the Lord hath in ſtore for all ungodly miſcreants, who by the abuſe of Gods patience, <hi>and their own impenitent hearts have ſo treaſured up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath, and revelation of the righteous Judgement of God, who will render to every man according to his deeds, Rom.</hi> 2.5, 6.</p>
            <p>To conclude this part; in a juſt diſpenſation of the ſeveral rewards of both; the great<note n="(h)" place="margin">Heb. 12.23.</note> Judge of all adorned with majeſty, attended with the glorious retinew of<note n="(i)" place="margin">Heb. 12.22.</note> innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Angels, and glorified<note n="(k)" place="margin">Dan. 7.10. S. Jud. v. 14.</note> Saints, ſeated upon his royall glorious throne, with<note n="(l)" place="margin">Mat. 25.31. Mat. 24.30.</note> power, great glory, ſhall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34671:26"/>call the one Sheep, and the other Goats, and making a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and everlaſting<note n="(m)" place="margin">Mat. 25.31, 32.</note> ſeparation between them ſhall ſay unto the one, <hi>Come ye bleſſed, inherit the Kingdome praepared for you, from the beginning of the world;</hi> and to the other, <hi>Go ye curſed into everlaſting fire;</hi> and theſe ſhall go away into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting puniſhment, but the righteous into life eternall.</p>
            <p>The ſum of all I find to be epitomized into theſe four Latine verſes:
<q>
                  <l>Quam triſtis vox eſt,<note place="margin">Vide hos ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus apud Ioh. Gerardum, tom. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> ſect. <hi>60.</hi>
                     </note> cum Iudex dixerit, Ite,</l>
                  <l>Tam duleis vox eſt, cum dixerit Ille, Venite.</l>
                  <l>Mortis, vel vitae breve verbum eſt, Ite, Venite,</l>
                  <l>Dicetur Reprobis, Ite; Venite, Piis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that this ſentence is like to that pillar of the cloud which was darkneſſe to the Egyptians, but light to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.20. The word, or ſentence of Life, or Death eternall it is but ſhort; yet curt and ſharp to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, or Caſtawayes; but ſhort, and ſweet to all Gods Elect, and Chriſts redeemed precious Holy ones.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> And thus, (my beloved Hearers) after my weak meaſure, though not (as I fully deſired) after the expectation happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſuch an auditory, I have diſpatch'd the Divinity, or Explication of the Text: It remains, now, that under the ſame favour of your continued patience, I deſcend to the morality, or the effectuall Application of the ſame: Thus much I ſhall aſſure you all, that I have it in my wiſhes, that my remaining words may fall like Manna upon every ear, and heart; for [that] they ſay, had a taſte, which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man did like, or wiſh for; I know its difficult to pleaſe all, yet it ſhall not be my aime (juſtly) to diſpleaſe any, only, my main intention is, to<note n="(n)" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> approve my ſelf to God, the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Heb. 12.23.</note> Judge of all, in the diſcharge of my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>And now, if any look that I ſhould, in the firſt place, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the boldneſſe to adviſe, or admoniſh theſe learned, and reverend Judges, who like <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> appearing [to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether] promiſe good to the Common-wealth, as that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriſme
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34671:26"/>doth to the Mariners at Sea; I ſhall diſappoint that expectation, ſith their great abilities, and their cordiall both aims and endeavours to do Juſtice [for Juſtice ſake] are ſo well known to the chiefeſt ſeats of Judicature, and to this Nation already: I ſhall therefore in ſtead of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them, take this occaſion to perſwade all you that hear me this day, to be enlarged towards God in thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, that by his propitious providence, he hath furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſeats of publique Juſtice with ſo accompliſhed Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates as theſe are: ſeeing therefore that by you we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy great<note n="(p)" place="margin">Act. 24.2, 3.</note> quietneſſe, and that very worthy deeds are done unto this Nation by your providence; we accept it alwayes, and in all places, (Honourable Lords) with all thankfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>My Admonitions muſt be directed unto all ſuch, who enjoy the benefit, and bleſſing of government, which in the juſt adminiſtration thereof is a Terrour to the wicked, lawleſſe, and ungodly; and an encouragement to thoſe that be good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3, 4. Yea, a<note n="(q)" place="margin">Xenophon <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Xenophon</hi> expreſſeth it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Thoſe who are good men, by behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the diſhonour caſt upon vicious perſons (by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Magiſtrate) for their unlawfull deeds, and their illegall perpetrations, do by ſarre more chearfully follow, and embrace vertue; and not only ſo, but exemplary Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice upon ſome proves a common terrour unto all; <hi>When a ſcorner is ſmitten, the ſimple will beware,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.25. or, as <hi>Moſes</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>When any praeſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinner was puniſhed, all Iſrael muſt hear, and fear, and do no more praeſumptuouſly, Deut.</hi> 17.12.13.</p>
            <p>To all the people in generall, then, let me ſay as <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet did by the mouth of <hi>Gehazi</hi> his ſervant to the <hi>Shu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namitiſh</hi> woman, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Behold thou haſt been carefull for us with all this care; What is to be done for thee?</hi> So ſay I, Behold our Governors have been carefull for you with all the care they can take, that you may every one dwell ſafely under your own<note n="(r)" place="margin">1 King. 4.25. Zech. 3.10.</note> Vines, and Fig-trees, in peace and quietneſſe; that there may be no<note n="(s)" place="margin">Pſal. 144.12, 13, 14.</note> leading into captivity, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in your ſtreets, but that your ſons may grow
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34671:27"/>up as Plants, and your daughters as the poliſhed corners of the Temple, that your ſheep may bring forth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and ten thouſands in your ſtreets, &amp;c. If ye aske me then, What is to be done for the Magiſtrates? I anſwer, They muſt be ſpoken for: If ye deſire to know, to whom? I anſwer, To the King of Heaven, even to that<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> King of Kings, of whoſe Kingdome there can be<note n="(u)" place="margin">Dan. 7.14 Luk. 1.33.</note> no end. If ye demand further, How this King of Heaven muſt be ſpoken to for them? I anſwer, or rather the great Apoſtle for me, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2. <hi>In ſupplications, and Prayers, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions:</hi> If you would know, for what? that ſame Text reſolves you; namely, <hi>that we may lead a quiet, and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe, and honeſty;</hi> intimating hereby, that men in lawfull authority are, (or ſhould be) the prime ſupporters both of Religion; and morall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and therefore being ſubject to many temptations, and undergoing many difficulties, they ſtand in need of many, and thoſe too the moſt fervent Prayers of all thoſe good people, who expect protection, ſupport, encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from them: Yea, if men did ſeriouſly ponder but the weight of the Magiſtrates office, they would double the zeal of their devotions for them: ſome of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> went ſo high in their expreſſions this way, as to ſay, <hi>qui funguntur magiſtratu non veniunt in judicium,</hi> as <hi>Paulus</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Paulus Fagius. ſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanor. <hi>3.</hi> Ben Syra.</note> 
               <hi>Fagius</hi> acquaints us to have been the ſentence of <hi>Rabbi Ben Syra,</hi> that is, ſuch as conſcientiouſly undergoe the office of Magiſtracy, were exempted from the Judgement to come; as if their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vigilancy, care, ſtudy, travell, and other laboriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which they underwent for the good, and weal of Community, had been ſo great, that it had after a ſort, excuſed them, for all things elſe: but we will take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this as an hyperbolicall expreſſion, and an exceſſive ſpeech in the <hi>Rabbi:</hi> Yet, nevertheleſſe, we read in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that <hi>Moſes</hi> (however then the<note n="(x)" place="margin">Num. 12.3.</note> meekeſt man upon earth) being in the office of a Governor, found cauſe to call it a [<note n="(y)" place="margin">Num. 11.11. confer, Exod. 18.22.</note> Burthen] yea, and to call out too for ſome<note n="(z)" place="margin">Num. 11.14.</note> help to ſtand under it: Pray we then to the God of wiſdome<note n="(*)" place="margin">Iſa. 28.6.</note> to be for a ſpirit of Judgement to them that ſit in Judgement, to inſpireour<note n="(a)" place="margin">Pſal. 105.22.</note> Senators with a ſpirit
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34671:27"/>of wiſdome, and counſell, to direct all their conſultations ſo, as they may in the iſſue tend to the glory of God, the credit of the Goſpell, the diſcovery,<note place="margin">2 King. 20 19.</note> and ſuppreſſion of Blaſphemy, Haereſie, Atheiſme, with the Authors of it, and for the eſtabliſhing of<note n="(b)" place="margin">Zech. 8.19.</note> Truth, with publick Peace, in the Nation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To the Magiſtrates there is due Honour belonging, to bee (beſides in the inward awfull thoughts of their power) manifeſted in Reverentiall ſpeeches, and Externall homage; you muſt nor revile the Gods; or as it is in your margine the Judges, nor curſe the Ruler of the people; it was the charge of <hi>Moſes</hi> a Prophet, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. Wherefore, when <hi>Paul</hi> had overſhot himſelfe, in a ſudden paſſion, that way, and given the nickname of a <hi>Whited wall</hi> to the High Prieſt (then his Judge), hee, upon advertiſement thereof, gave himſelf a check for it, upon the conſideration of that very text, <hi>Act.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Moſes</hi> a chief Governour is ſtyled by <hi>Joſhua [My Lord]</hi> Moſes, <hi>Num.</hi> 11.28. and the people in taken of civill homage, and obſervance, [bow the knee] to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor in <hi>Aegypt, Gen.</hi> 41.43. And moreover (which for ſome reaſons, I will not omit to note on this occaſion) for the greater gracefulneſſe of their Office and Perſons, they have been, in all Ages, arrayed in robes of Majeſty, and honour before the people; chiefly when placed in the Seat of Judicature, and under the actuall execution of their ſo honorable Function; which may be gathered from 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.10. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.29.</p>
            <p>Render then honor to the Magiſtrate, to whom it is ſo many wayes due, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. and it's well obſerved by <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> that the Apoſtle ſaith not ſimply, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Give,</hi> as if the thing were Arbitrary; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="*" place="margin">See Matt. 22.21. &amp; Luk. 20.25.</note> 
               <hi>render</hi> it, as of Duty, in all obedience to Authority.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there is due to the publick Magiſtrates<note n="(c)" place="margin">Matt. 17.25. Rom. 13.7.</note> Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and Cuſtome, appertaining to them for all their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick care, providence, protection; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they attending continually upon this very ſame thing, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying publick ſpirits in their publick places, being conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34671:28"/>not only to ſpend, but to be<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.15.</note> ſpent for the good of the Community the words in the originall Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, put for Tribute, and Cuſtome, in a generality of uſe are oft-times confounded, and indifferently put to ſignifie any kind of payment made to the Governors; yet critically ſay ſome learned Authors, Tribute is of that which ariſeth out of what is grown within the land, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from being carryed, or brought into the Exchequer, or Treaſury appointed: Cuſtome is that which is paid for what is, according to Contracts in Traffique, imported or expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, into, or out of a Nation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo<note n="(d)" place="margin">Strabo. lib. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Strabo</hi> calls ſuch things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> word <hi>vectigal</hi> hath its name <hi>ex vectura:</hi> But before ſo learned an Auditory, I may not waſte time about words:<note n="(e)" place="margin">Bodinus, l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> de Republ.</note> 
               <hi>Bodinus</hi> reckons up divers kinds of both; the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the manner, or of the meaſure of either, whether ordinary, or extraordinary, is left to the prudence and piety of lawfull Superiours, according as the ſtate of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant affaires, the faculty and ability of the people, or the neceſſity of Subſidiary ſupplies, for the ſupport, honor, and ſafety of a Common-wealth may require: Now, an obedient people may aſſure themſelves, that aequall, juſt, and godly Governors, will not <hi>turn Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into gall, Amos</hi> 6.12. but remember, that God, (for<note n="(f)" place="margin">Chr. 19 6.</note> whom they judge) is pleaſed to ſtyle them<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 44.28. Numb. 27.17.</note> Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, whoſe office is not to<note n="(h)" place="margin">Mic. 3 3. Ezek. 45.</note> flay off the skin from off the backs of the flock, but to ſhear the ſheep ſo for their own uſe, that withall the wool may grow again for the warmth of the flock it ſelf; even as it's reported to have been the ſaying of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> A good Shepheard ſhould <hi>tondere pecus, non deglubere,</hi> as<note n="(i)" place="margin">Sueton in <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Suetonius</hi> records it: Oppreſſion (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) maketh even a wiſe man<note n="(k)" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.7.</note> mad, yea, and it may make a good man<note n="(l)" place="margin">Exod. 2.23. Pſal. 12.5.</note> ſigh: But when (as I noted in my former Sermon) theſe things are expected, and impoſed, after the old Charter of <hi>England, ſalvo contenemento,</hi> in a tender moderation, Tribute muſt be rendred to whom it is due; our Saviour himſelf paid it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.25. and ſuch payment was in uſe even in the days of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34671:28"/>
            <p>In ſumme, who doe, or ſhould, carefully guard your Religion, your Poſſeſſions, but Governors? Who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect you by land, and fenſe you by ſea, but they? And what can you bethink to purchaſe a ſolid peace on the land? or to fortifie your wooden walls at ſea? And if Governours lay out themſelves for the good of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, ſo that themſelves ſhall become a generall, and a publick good; it will be a great Ingratitude in thoſe who reap the comfort, not to yeeld ſuch all lawfull aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
            <p>And thus having ſhewn the duties of the people at large, in their relation to Governors, and to Government: It onely remains, that I adde but a few words more, ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the preſent ſeaſon, and occaſion of this meeting.</p>
            <p>And here I might begin my advice to Mr. High<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Iohn Trott <hi>of</hi> Laverſtake <abbr>Esq</abbr>
               </note> Sheriff: but why ſhould I goe about to paint a Diamond, or to enamell a pearle? whoſe modeſty whileſt it declined Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, it overtook him: He hath ſet a faire Copy for his Succeſſors in that Office, and Authority, to write after: I ſhall onely deſire him to continue doing as hee doth doe, and then both his<note n="(m)" place="margin">Cant. 1.3</note> Name, and his Actions ſhall bee as an Oyntment poured forth to perſume Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity as with ſome fragrant odour, that may provoke Imitation.</p>
            <p>I might next direct my Exhortation to the Gentlemen of the Grand Inqueſt, upon whoſe Information,<note place="margin">Advice to the Grand Jury.</note> and Preſentments depends almoſt the main tranſaction of the preſent proceedings in Judicature, for the<note n="(n)" place="margin">Gal. 5.12.</note> cutting off of incorrigible Malefactors, and the reformation of all diſorders, and illegall irregularities; If you would bee eſteemed as the Eyes of your whole Countrey, you had need to ſee clearly; but if in any particulars you would defire to be of Lyncean, and diſcerning eyes indeed, Let me deſire you to have ſpeciall regard to the Violators of Gods ſacred, and precious<note n="(o)" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.2.</note> Ordinances, in the promoting whereof, as you ſhall advance the glory of God, and therein your own felicity, ſo (as I am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly perſwaded) extremely gratifie theſe learned, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34671:29"/>religious Judges, to whom nothing is more dean, then the promotion of Gods<note n="(p)" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> Honor: one thing, above many others, that I might mind you of, is the Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of thoſe Artifriall, and Grand Impoſtors, or Church-cheaters, the Jeſuites, by whoſe cunning in ſinn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, (under the ſeverall habits, or ſhapes, as well of Mechanicks, as otherwiſe) it's more than probable, that all the combuſtions, at the preſent, in the Chriſtian world are raiſed, and not a little in Great <hi>Britany;</hi> if you have your owne ſoules, the proſperity, and welfare of the Church, and State of <hi>England,</hi> uſe your beſt indeavours to detect, and to preſent thoſe Stygian, and Infernall Emiſſaries, for their mature extirpation; Take heed, and doe it.</p>
            <p>And as for you Jurors of another order,<note place="margin">Advice to the Petty-Jury and Witneſſes.</note> and all thoſe who are in any kind of Cauſes to give Evidence; I hope none of you are become <hi>Antinomians,</hi> to reject,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Pſal. 119.126.</note> or evacuate the Morall law of God, if not, then bee mindfull of the Third Commandement, wherein you cannot but take notice, how upon no terms, the Lord hath proteſted to hold him<note n="(r)" place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note> guiltieſſe, who by raſh, or<note n="(s)" place="margin">Zech. 8.17.</note> falſe Oaths ſhalt dare to take his Name in vain, or conteſt his dreadfull Omniſcence to an injuſtice: againſt all<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.10.</note> [perjured] perſons the Law ſtands in full force, and vigor, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. The very Heathens had their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Perjury-revenging Gods, to whoſe vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive powers they left the Violators of their Deities, as if themſelves were at a loſſe how to proportion a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſo foul a crime: And grave men are of opinion, that in taking Oaths men are to look to the ſenſe of the Impoſer, otherwiſe they doe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſwear falſely; and if they performe not what is ſworn by them, they doe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, forſwear and perjure themſelves: It's ſad, when amongſt Chriſtians that Apophthegme in <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſtall be made uſe of, in good earneſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that Children are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened with Rattles, and Men with Oaths: But I hope<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 6.9.</note> Better things of you.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:34671:29"/>
            <p>I had prepared alſo ſome more viands for ſome other<note n="*" place="margin">The Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers.</note> gueſts, but finding them not preſent, it's poſſible their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs are not up ſo early, or, perhaps, with ſome of them <hi>durum potabile</hi> may go down ſweeter, then the gold of the Sanctuary, to which Gods word is reſembled <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.10.</p>
            <p>To my reverend Brethren of the Miniſtry,<note place="margin">To the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</note> I ſhal not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay much, only to the learned, and godly among them be a ſhort Remembrancer of perſiſting in the great and important Labour of<note n="(u)" place="margin">Col 4.17.</note> Fulfilling their Miniſtry, in which regard I wiſh from my heart, that we might be all as ſo many Coloſſian<note n="(w)" place="margin">Cor. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>Archippuſſes:</hi> Times have been, when with too many ſound Preaching hath been eſteemed, but a ſound of Preaching; and whereas S <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſed of himſelf, and of his fellow-labourers, <hi>We</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">2 Cor 4.5</note> 
               <hi>preach not our ſelves, but Chriſt Jeſus and him</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor 3.11 Gal. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>Crucified,</hi> the ſaying might have been inverted, we our ſelves preach not; and yet, (upon what pretence who knowes?) like ſome Anticks in old buildings they with <hi>Iſſachar</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">Gen. 49.14.</note> couched down, and bended the ſhoulders, as if the whole ſtreſſe of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call building had layn upon their ſhoulders.</p>
            <p>Let us have not only our<note n="(z)" place="margin">Exod. 28.33.</note> Bels, but alſo our<note n="(a)" place="margin">Exod. 28.34</note> Pomegranates, our Bels to tole, and call men into the Temple of piety, but our Pomegranates as emblemes of our fruitfull converſations; and as <hi>Aaron</hi> the Prieſt had the names of the twelve Tribes engraven upon his<note n="(b)" place="margin">Exod. 28.21.</note> Breaſtplate, thereby to intimate the dear, and hearty affection, that, as one that<note n="(c)" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> watched for their ſouls, he ſhould bear to them all; ſo let us have all the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our charge, in our<note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2.8.</note> hearts, as if our very<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 3.8.</note> life, and welfare were bound up in their ſpirituall<note n="(f)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.1.</note> Proficiency: The Schoolemen are ſomewhat divided in opinion about Theology, or Divinity, whether it be a Science? and if ſo, of what kinde? <hi>Thomas</hi> makes <hi>Theologiam, ſpeculativam; Scotus, practicam; Hales, affectivam;</hi> but, as when three ſtarres are in conjunction, there uſually followeth ſome admirable effect, ſo where there is a concurrence of all theſe, they make up an accompliſhed Divine: Well then, let us lift up our voices like<note n="(g)" place="margin">Iſa. 58.1.</note> Trumpets, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaks; and why like Trumpets? are there not other
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34671:30"/>ſounds as loud? Loe, the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Pſal. 29.3.</note> Thunder of the Lord giveth out a<note n="(i)" place="margin">Pſ. 77.17, 18.</note> voice, and that a mighty voice; yea, the Sea<note n="(k)" place="margin">Pſ. 93.7.</note> roars, and makes a very loud noiſe; yet not like Thunder, nor like the Sea, which both are louder, but lift up we our voices like Trumpets, becauſe in ſounding of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, the Hand is uſed, as well as the Mouth, to intimate, that a preacher muſt take heed to<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Tim 4.16. Read</hi> Ho ker lib. <hi>5.</hi> Eccleſ. polit. ſect. <hi>81.</hi> per tot.</note> himſelf in matter of Action, as well as to his Doctrine, in matter of Elocution; as <hi>Noah</hi> is obſerved to have taught the old world as well by his<note n="(m)" place="margin">Heb. 11.7.</note> hand, in building the Arke, as by his lips in forewarning their deſtruction, and both conjoyned gave him the denomination of a Preacher of Righteouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Verbum ſapientibus;</hi> and I crave pardon for this boldneſſe.</p>
            <p>To end this Diſcourſe, and leſt I be further<note n="(n)" place="margin">Act. 24.4.</note> tedious unto you: To all this people in generall, let me ſay, as S. <hi>Jan.</hi> 2.12. <hi>So ſpeak ye; and ſo do, as they that ſhall be judged by the Law of liberty:</hi> ye have heard the certainty, and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality of all your Diſſolutions, and the ſame likewiſe of all your Reſurrections: ye have heard moreover of Books, and Regiſters wherein ſtand recorded all your thoughts, words, and actions whatſoever done in the Body, and according to what is written in thoſe Books, ye muſt all be Judged at the laſt day: ſo then, be exhorted all of you, from the higheſt to the loweſt, to labour to keep theſe Books, theſe laſting Records clear; and remember, that here Heaven is either won, or loſt; after death men are, ſay Schoolemen, <hi>Extra ſtatum merendi, &amp; demerendi,</hi> out of a condition to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure any thing by acting, as who are then in a ſtate, or condition to receive their ſeverall<note n="(o)" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> rewards, whether of good, or ill, according as they have done before in the body: wherefore as our Saviour, <hi>Let us work the works of God, whileſt it is Day, Joh</hi> 9.4. that is, as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, during the continuance of the Day of this Life: Take notice that your Time, and your Day is<note n="(p)" place="margin">Pſ. 39 4, 5.</note> ſhort, your account large, and the Judge before whom this<note n="(q)" place="margin">Rom. 14.12.</note> Account is to be given up,<note n="(r)" place="margin">Mat. 25.24.</note> ſtrict, and<note n="(s)" place="margin">2 Tim 4.8.</note> juſt, and no<note n="(t)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.17.</note> Reſpecter of perſons at all.</p>
            <p>In one word, to cloſe up all; act vigorouſly for God,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34671:30"/>for his Chriſt, for his Goſpell, and that as well in the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and Duties thereof, as in the Priviledges, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the ſame; be as well reſolved to have Chriſt for a Lord to rule thee, as for a Jeſus to ſavethee: In ſumme, as I ſaid in the concluſion of my laſt Sermon, in this very place, on the ſame occaſion; So live, and ſtrive for holineſſe, as if thou hadſt no mean of ſalvation but that; I mean, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of zealous earneſtneſſe, and Chriſtian endevours: And yet ſo reſt, and relye upon the merits of Jeſus Chriſt, as if, in point of ſelf-deſert (which is nothing) thou hadſt no holineſſe at all: This, this alone is the way, by grace to arrive at glory.</p>
            <closer>Amen, Amen.
Soli Deo Gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 5. lin. 38. read <hi>Protoplaſts.</hi> p. 11. l. 3. r. <hi>mortality.</hi> p. 11. l. 3 r. <hi>appoſite.</hi> p. 19. l, 4. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 23. l. 6. r. <hi>muſt be by beleevers.</hi> p. 28. l. 25. r. for <hi>ſerenity, dexterity.</hi> p. 43. l. 19. r. Rom. 13.3, 4. <hi>and as Xenophon.</hi> p. 48. l. 23. r. <hi>Omniſcience.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
